========================
纪录片之家倾情奉献
www.jlpzj.net
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
========================
翻译, 校订: Hugh
埃尔顿•约翰到松林制片厂的时间是…
Elton John, up at Pinewood on--
- 什么时候来着? - 12号
- What's the date? - The 12th of--
3月12号
Twelfth of March.
这里是20… 30帧分轨中心
It's me, split track, 20-- Thirty-frame center track.
就是这个调
There's the tone.
请安静
Quiet, please.
1984-1994十年间，一场融天时地利人和的完美风暴
彻底改变了整个动画行业的面貌
开始
Here we go.
埃尔顿·约翰爵士
那是1994年的春天
It was the spring of 1994
我们即将完成狮子王的制作
and we were just finishing The Lion King,
这部电影好评如潮
which would go on to earn great reviews
并赚取了7.5亿美元的票房
and about three-quarters of a billion dollars at the box office.
对迪斯尼的新员工来说 这是个好消息
Not bad for a group of artists who were kicked off the Disney lot
该片也算是挽回了2D动画江河日下的颓势
and an art form that was given up for dead just ten years earlier.
我是狮子王的制片人
I produced The Lion King
当时, 剧组人员即将举行首发见面会
and the cast-and-crew premiere was coming up fast.
按照惯例, 大家会逐一登台致感谢词
It was tradition for all of us to get up on-stage and give warm thank-you speeches.
这一次, 我决定把致谢演讲拍下来
But this time I decided to film all the speeches instead.
开始拍了?
You are rolling?
- 是的 - 好
- Yeah. - Okay.
在公司的各项业务中, 很明显…
With all the many varied businesses this company is in, it is clear--
迈克尔·埃斯纳
迪斯尼公司CEO
动画将日渐成为我们的灵魂与核心
It becomes clearer every day that animation is its soul, heart,
是我们的主体业务
and most of its body parts.
过去这些年, 你们表现得很出色
You guys have done an unbelievable job over the last decade,
完成了佳作狮子王, 推动了公司发展
culminating in Lion King, in pushing forward the company,
彰显了文化的魅力与艺术的气质
the culture and the quality of artistry.
我要代表我本人, 公司董事会, 股东, 以及我的孩子
Congratulations from me, from anybody who is not on this tape,
向你们表示祝贺
from our board, our shareholders and my children.
恭喜大家
Congratulations.
谢谢 谢谢大家
Thank you. Thanks, everybody.
感谢大家奉献的精彩作品
Thank you to everybody for another absolutely incredible job
希望能再接再厉, 再创辉煌
on another marvelous movie on the way to the next great movie.
外界看来, 这一切都很完美
To an outsider, it looked like a perfect world.
但是在幕后
But backstage,
气氛已十分紧张
the tension had reached a peak.
谢谢, 可以了吗?
Thank you. Okay?
尽管我们刚取得了前所未有的成功
Even though it was the moment of our greatest success,
但已经是山雨欲来风满楼了
the wheels were coming off the car.
下面我来细讲故事的来龙去脉
This is the story of how we got there.
片名：唤醒睡美人
让我们回到80年代初期
Let's back up to the early '80s
加州伯班克市的迪斯尼制片场
on the Disney Studio lot in Burbank, California.
我们的乐队正向同事们传递着假日的喜悦
The animation band is spreading its holiday cheer to the employees
一如既往, 主奏乐器是班卓琴和单簧琴
with banjos and jew's harps, as was the tradition.
右边这个人就是我
And that's me on the right,
正用贝斯弹着铃儿响叮当
trying to play"Jingle Bells" On the bass.
与同龄人一样, 我是看着迪斯尼电影长大的
Like so many of us, I grew up on a diet of Disney films.
每过四年, 我就会像朝圣一样
And every four years, I'd make a pilgrimage
奔向露天影院一睹迪斯尼最新大作的风采
to the drive-in theater to see their latest animated masterpiece.
20岁时, 我在迪斯尼工作室觅得一份差事
When I was 20, I got a job at the studio
负责给动画制作人端茶送水
delivering artwork and coffee to the animators
为此我已感觉欣喜若狂
and I felt like I won the lottery.
这就是沃特建的房子
This was the house that Walt built.
沃特•迪斯尼, 好莱坞骄子, 打造迪斯尼乐园的天才
Walt Disney, the toast of Hollywood, the genius behind Disneyland
还制作了第一部动画电影: 白雪公主
and the producer behind the first animated feature, Snow White.
到了五十年代, 沃特渐渐失去了对动画的兴趣
By the 1950s, Walt was losing interest in animation
更多地开始关注真人电影
and his attention turned to live-action films,
新兴的电视媒体
the new medium of television,
首座迪斯尼主题公园的建设
and building the first theme park, Disneyland,
而且计划着未来都市的图景
and planning futuristic cities of tomorrow.
目前为止, 我们佛罗里达计划最重要的部分
By far, the most important part of our Florida Project,
也是迪斯尼世界的核心内容
in fact, the heart of everything we'll be doing in Disney World,
将是我们的“明日世界实验原型”, 即“未来世界”
will be our Experimental Prototype City of Tomorrow, Epcot.
沃特1966年去世
Walt died in 1966,
但迪斯尼仍在为孩子们制作着天真烂漫的卡通片
but the studio still made sweet, harmless, animated comedies for kids,
监制人是一群大师级动画制作人, 被称为“九长老”
supervised by his master animators, the Nine Old Men,
出品人是沃特的女婿, 工作室头号人物罗恩•米勒
and produced by Walt's son-in-law, studio head Ron Miller.
我是兰迪•卡特莱特, 这是罗恩•米勒
I'm Randy Cartwright and this is Ron Miller.
兰迪, 你好啊, 很高兴见到你
Randy! How are you? Good to see you.
这是兰迪, 电影开了个好头
This is Randy. Great way to start the film.
- 这是… 你的第一支广告吗?  - 没错
- Is this a new--? Your first commercial? - Ha, ha. Yup.
拍这个干嘛?
What is this for?
- 家庭电影而已 - 纪录片
- Just home movie. - It's a documentary.
关于工作室的纪录片
Documentary of the animation studio.
妈妈, 你好
Hi, Mom.
很好, 开了个好头
Well, we're off to a good start.
现在是1980年4月9日
Here it is, April 9th, 1980.
我们要去采访大家了
This is the past to all you folks out there.
我们马上进去, 看看大家在干嘛, 跟我来
And we're gonna go inside and see what it's like. Come on.
不知为何, 迪斯尼公司大楼的走道里
For some reason, the halls of the Disney Animation building
总是弥漫着冷却器, 铅笔屑和旧油毡的味道
always smelled faintly of swamp coolers and pencil shavings and old linoleum.
这就是臭名昭著的老鼠窝
This is the infamous Rat's Nest.
动画长期以来都是在这样的地方制作
Animation had been in this slow downward spiral for a long time,
沃特在世时就一直这样
even since Walt Disney was alive.
老一辈退休后, 加州艺术学院的年轻毕业生
As veteran animators retired, new kids, mostly from the Disney-sponsored school,
开始挑起工作室大梁
CalArts, filled the hallways.
鲁本, 你也是加艺毕业的吧
Why, Ruben, you're from CalArts also.
没错, 你是哪位?
Right. And who are you?
- 我? - 没错
- Me? - Yes.
我是约翰•雷斯特
I'm John Lasseter.
他是个摄像的, 马上就会走
He's the cameraman. He's leaving in a little while.
要看看我的动画吗?
Could I show you animation?
- 要看看我的动画吗? - 这就是动画
- Could I show you animation? - This is animation.
我翻些东西给你看
Could I flip something for you?
就是这个, 看好了, 彼得•潘
This is it. Look at that. Peter Pan.
看着…
Oh, looks up and...
这比我们今天做的还精彩
It's better than the magic we're making today,
但我们也做不了什么
but we can't help that.
我们是一群精力过剩, 需要发泄的人
We were full of a lot of pent-up youthful creative energy that had to go somewhere,
而发泄渠道通常是: 长时间的午餐, 排球
so it was channeled into things like long lunches, volleyball games,
年度讽刺漫画展
the annual caricature show,
以及我最爱的
and my perennial favorite,
艾迪•费舍和桃乐思•黛的假日秀
the holiday show that starred Eddie Fisher and Doris Day, for some unknown reason.
这是我们的动画师罗恩•克莱门茨
This is one of our animators here. This is Ron Clements.
他正在制作狐狸与猎狗中关于寡妇的场景
He's working on a scene of the Widow from The Fox and the Hound.
- 不可思议, 这位是约翰•马斯克 - 谢谢, 谢谢
- Magically, here is Mr. John-ald Musker. - Thank you, thank you.
他也是我们工作室的动画师
Another animator here at the magic factory.
这是格兰•基恩
This is Glen Keane.
他是一名指导动画师
He is a directing animator.
我早上8点就来了
I've been here since 8:00 this morning.
嘿, 蒂姆, 这是蒂姆•伯顿
Hi, Tim. This is Tim Burton,
也是我们的同事
another one of our people here.
罗恩•米勒清楚动画师的职业生涯不长
Ron Miller knew that Walt's guys were retiring fast.
所以他必须不断启用新人
He had to raise a new crop of animators,
同时也必须小心谨慎
but he was cautious about it.
五年前的一件事令他大为光火
He got burned five years earlier
当时他满怀信任地把动画部交给唐•布鲁斯主管
when he entrusted a charismatic animator named Don Bluth to lead the department.
但布鲁斯这个人争议很大
But Bluth polarized the animators.
崇拜者奉他为行业救世主
Some adored him as the messiah of animation and others...
反对者则视其为自大狂
Well, others thought he was just another Walt wannabe.
讽刺的是, 布鲁斯自己也对公司动画部失去了信心
lronically, Bluth himself became disillusioned with the studio's Animation Department.
所以, 他在1979年生日时, 选择了辞职
So on his birthday in 1979, he resigned
而且, 他带走了一半的动画师, 另立门户
and took half the animators with him to start his own studio.
这场变故让狐狸与猎狗延期半年完成
The bombshell set back the release of The Fox and the Hound by six months
米勒和整个工作室就这样惨遭背叛
and left Miller and the studio betrayed.
当时迪斯尼存在着有趣的隔代现象
It was this interesting cross-generational thing
一边是老一辈的传奇动画师
where you still had a few of these legendary Disney artists
他们年逾花甲, 即将退休
who were now in their sixties and approaching retirement
另一边则是一群二十来岁的年轻人
and then a bunch of young people in their twenties
他们对动画充满了简单真挚的激情与热爱
who were really, really excited and sort of passionate about this medium.
前辈的悉心教导当然很好
It was thrilling to learn from the masters.
但大家总觉得
But there was a feeling like
我们可以做出更好的作品
that somehow we could be making better films.
当时, 公司做了一份调查
Around that time, the studio did a survey
发现很大部分青少年观影者
that revealed a majority of teenage moviegoers
对迪斯尼影片表示厌恶
wouldn't be caught dead near a Disney movie.
我们就这样等待, 希望变革来临
We were just waiting, waiting for something, anything to happen.
周一, 我们报道了迪斯尼工作室
On Monday, we reported that Walt Disney Studios
正面临财务困境
was on shaky financial ground,
因为其表现乏力的电影业务
because of its troubled Film Division
以及盈利不佳的未来世界项目
and weak earnings from the Epcot Center in Florida.
然而, 之后事态发生了戏剧性的变化
However, since that report, there have been dramatic developments.
短短的四日内, 迪斯尼股价飙升了16%
In just four days, Disney stock jumped 16 percent,
达到每股58美元的高价
topping off at around $58 a share.
分析人士为该事件给出两点解释
Analysts attribute the jump to two factors.
美人鱼 - 一部融合曼哈顿与童话的青春喜剧片
Splash, the youth-oriented comedy about a mermaid in Manhattan,
以上映三天600万的票房震惊了电影界
stunned Hollywood by racking up over $6 million in its opening three days.
它成为了迪斯尼吸金最快的电影
That's the best opening for any movie in Disney's history.
另一大意外, 是罗伊•迪斯尼辞去董事长职务
Another surprise, the resignation of Roy E. Disney as chairman of the board.
他是沃特的侄子, 是沃特弟弟所生
He's Walt's nephew and son of Walt's brother,
也是公司创始人之一
the company's co-founder.
公司真正的业务中心, 曾经是
The real heartbeat of this company was,
现在是, 将来也永远是电影
is and will always be the film business.
因为电影是一切创意的源泉
Because from the film business comes the ideas
这些创意可以应用到主题公园中
that then generate new things in the parks.
可以推动新的营销, 新的…
New promotions, new--
总之就是公司保持新鲜生命的源动力
A kind of a sense of continuing newness about the company in general.
当我们电影做得不好时
And when that began to fail--
我们就会开始渐渐
And I actually, somewhere along the line,
听到流言蜚语
began hearing things like,
“我看, 他们根本就无心做电影了,
"Well, I don't think they really wanna stay in the movie business,
拍得总是马马虎虎, 我们也根本不想看了
because it's not doing very well and we don't really even need it anyway."
这些话令我很苦恼, 因为我…
And that gave me all sorts of problems, because I, you know--
我记得有人说
I remember saying at one point,
“如果你真那么想,
"Well, if you really think that way,
那你就真的离电影太远了。”
then what you're doing is running a museum."
人们嘲讽罗伊为“沃特的笨侄子”
People always talked about Roy as the idiot nephew.
“笨侄子”成了他的绰号
That was his nickname.
而事实并非如此
Nothing could be really further from the truth.
他聪明, 谦逊且雷厉风行
He was smart, unassuming and powerful.
你很容易低估他
You could easily underestimate him,
但低估他是很危险的
but you did so at your own peril.
1984年
In 1984,
专做蓄意收购的索尔•斯坦伯格盯上了迪斯尼
the corporate raider Saul Steinberg turned his sights on Disney.
他扬言要买下整家公司
He threatened to buy the company,
然后分拆出售获利
break it up and sell the parts for a profit.
作为回应, 迪斯尼董事会决定
The board countered by paying
高价回购斯坦伯格所持股票
Steinberg a premium to buy back his shares.
迪斯尼被耍了
It was greenmail.
多年后, 罗伊和他表弟罗恩•米勒
For years, Roy and his cousin-in-law, Ron Miller,
在董事局会议上相向而坐
sat across the boardroom table.
他们为一件事争执不下
And now the two were at odds with
那就是董事会当年对威胁收购的处理
how the board was handling the takeover threat.
会议最后得出结论
And we finally came to the conclusion
我们身在局内, 别无选择
that we can't do anything on the inside,
虽然我反对, 但毕竟孤掌难鸣
because I'm the lone voice of dissent on this board.
所以我选择向董事会请辞
So I resigned from the board of directors.
我的辞呈引起了很多关注
And it got enormous amounts of attention.
第二天早上, 我收到了
I had a stack the next morning of phone messages
无数的电话留言
that probably was three, four inches deep.
其中一条来自迈克尔•埃斯纳
One of the messages in that stack was Eisner.
他差不多在事件发生一年多前加入董事会
And I had known Michael because he'd come maybe a
那之前, 我就在艺术学院里认识他了
year before that on to the board at CalArts.
迈克尔不是商科出身, 他是英语专业的
Michael wasn't an M.B.A. He was an English major.
他在纽约长大
He grew up in New York,
早年的工作
where one of his first jobs
是为电视台制作儿童节目
was programming kids' television for ABC.
他在派拉蒙工作期间取得过骄人的业绩
And Michael had an amazing track record coming from Paramount.
参与过奥斯卡获奖影片《母女情深》的制作
He'd had hits, Oscar nominations, Terms of Endearment.
他接手迪斯尼时, 正春风得意
He was a winner when he was hired to come in and run Disney.
但他有时也会把事情搞砸
He also was a man who liked to blow things up.
是弗兰克•威尔斯建议罗伊
It was Frank Wells that gave
让迈克尔担任董事局主席
Roy the idea of making Michael the chairman.
弗兰克与罗伊
Frank and Roy were
早年在波莫纳大学是同班同学
classmates at Pomona College in the early '50s.
我觉得弗兰克更像个精明的商人
I thought, you know, Frank's more of a businessman
迈克尔则学究气重些
and Michael is a little nuts.
他们两人的组合
And the two together kind of
让我想起沃特和我父亲
in some ways made me think of Walt and my dad.
于是我们想知道, “你们二人打算怎么做?”
So we began saying, "How would you two like to take this job?"
迪斯尼王国管理层进行了变动重组
There's been a management shake-up in the Magic Kingdom of Disney.
两位好莱坞高管被举荐
Two Hollywood studio executives have been chosen
掌管迪斯尼公司
to run Walt Disney Productions,
这是迪斯尼第一次由外人担任最高层
the first time outsiders have been brought in at the top.
迪斯尼董事会推选来自派拉蒙的迈克尔•埃斯纳为主席
The Disney board of directors chose Michael Eisner of Paramount Pictures as chairman,
以及华纳兄弟的弗兰克•威尔斯为首席运营官
and Frank Wells of Warner Bros. As chief operating officer.
新晋管理层的第一要务
The first goal, really, of new management
就是认真地重振电影业务
is gonna be getting back in the movie business in a very serious way,
不能马马虎虎, 拍完了事
in the sense of not only just making movies,
要有新的想法和创意
but coming up with new ideas.
二人的组合确实让公司变得与众不同
Their partnership really made the company special.
人们看来, 迈克尔行事鲁莽
There was this perception that Michael was a shoot-from-the-hip,
为人不拘小节
back-of-the-napkin kind of guy,
弗兰克则工整细致, 井井有条
and Frank was very organized and ran things in an orderly manner.
但很多时候, 事实恰恰相反
But in many ways, it was the opposite.
迈克尔更为正常理性
Michael was kind of the sane one.
而弗兰克常做些出格疯狂的事
And Frank, he did bold and crazy things,
比如横渡海洋, 攀登世界各大著名山峰
like swimming oceans, climbing the great summits of the world
甚至于半夜三点打电话问人高飞的本名
and calling at 3 a.M. To ask what Goofy's original name was.
我们欢迎迪斯尼的登山勇士, 弗兰克•威尔斯
Please welcome my mountain-climbing Disney teammate, Frank Wells.
这次员工论坛让我明白
I figured out from this employee forum what the difference is
首席执行官(CEO)与首席运营官(COO)的区别
between chief operating officer and chief executive officer.
COO负责完成一些危险动作
Chief operating officer is in charge of doing dangerous things,
比如说我就要吊在钢丝上跟小叮当一起飞
like when I have to fly here with Tinker Bell on a tiny wire.
CEO, 则负责搞笑
Chief executive officer, he's in charge of funny.
弗兰克?
Frank?
嘿, 迈克尔
Hi, Michael.
1984年我回到公司
I came back to the company in 1984
有些漫不经心地对迈克尔说
and, rather cavalier way at the time, said to Michael,
“为何不让我来掌管动画部
"Why don't you let me have the Animation Department,
因为我现在是很珍贵的
because I may be the only guy right now,
新人们不断加入以后
with all these new people coming in,
熟悉整个流程, 又认识大部分人的, 恐怕只有我了
who at least understands the process and knows most of the people."
当时的制作工艺正逐渐被淘汰
The state of the art at that moment was kind of waning
工作室对老式工艺也不是特别依赖
and the enthusiasm of the studio itself towards it had not been real strong.
所以我有些关心这个问题
So I just felt a little protective about it.
我来到约翰•马斯克的办公室
And I was in John Musker's office.
记得之后史蒂夫•休利特走进来
And I think it was Steve Hulett came in
告诉我们罗恩•米勒辞职了
with the memo saying that Ron Miller had resigned.
我们都很震惊, 一时难以接受
And we were shocked and it was a huge bombshell to go off.
但我心里明白, 这是个大好消息
But I thought it was, you know, terrific news,
这可能意味着
that maybe it meant that things
工作室要往好的方向发展
were gonna actually get better at the studio.
约翰应该跟我想的一样
And John, I think, felt the same way.
他看起来非常高兴
He seemed pretty excited about it.
而罗恩则有些忧伤地说
But Ron was worried, in a sort of melancholy mood, said,
“永远不要高兴得太早”
"It could always get worse."
这是一次来自好莱坞的入侵
It was an invasion from Hollywood.
停车场排满了宝马和保时捷
The parking lot was jammed with BMWs and Porsches.
我记得装修工拆的那些墙
And I remember interior decorators tearing down walls
是1939年后, 就不曾变过的
that hadn't been touched since 1939.
全新的贝伯地毯取代了使用多年的油毡
New Berber carpeting replaced decades-old linoleum.
我不知道油毡有什么不好的
I couldn't figure out what's wrong with linoleum.
要知道, 沃特•迪斯尼当年就走在那油毡上
I mean, Walt Disney walked on that linoleum.
甚至连零食贩卖机也被拆了
Even the snack machines were being torn out.
再见, 售货机
Goodbye, vending machines.
当时, 我还不擅长跟好莱坞打交道
I had no experience with Hollywood at that time.
之前跟我打交道的都是和蔼的老一辈
My experience was with kindly old men with cardigan sweaters.
他们通常心平气和, 慈眉善目
And they would sit around and pat you on the back.
现在的这帮家伙
And here's these guys hollering
则是口无遮拦, 脏话连篇
foul language in the middle of story meetings.
这像一泼冷水, 突然把我惊醒
And a splash of cold water, suddenly a wake-up to reality.
把我带回现实
You're in the real world here.
大家好, 我是迈克尔•埃斯纳
Hello. I'm Michael Eisner.
欢迎来到迪斯尼周日电影秀
And welcome to The Disney Sunday Movie.
迈克尔•埃斯纳是迪斯尼那一批人中
Michael Eisner is the irreverent kid from the Disney generation
最不守规矩的
who has taken over the toy store.
迪斯尼也让他变得家财万贯
The money alone is right out of Fantasyland.
他的薪酬和股份价值千万美元
His salary and stock options are worth tens of millions of dollars.
在迪斯尼周日电影秀中
He may look every inch the company chairman
他可能看起来一本正经
when he is taping the introduction to The Disney Sunday Night Movie.
但实际上, 他是所有人中玩得最开心的
But in fact, he's having more fun than any other boy on the block.
瞧, 米奇, 我们的朋友也来了
Look, Mickey. Some of our friends are coming.
嘿, 米妮
Hey, Minnie.
迈克尔上任CEO后的第一步
So one of the first things that Michael did as CEO
就是将他派拉蒙的旧部杰弗里•卡岑伯格招入麾下
was to bring in Jeffrey Katzenberg, his colleague from Paramount,
让他掌管迪斯尼的电影部
to run the Film Division of Disney.
杰弗里早年在纽约从政
Jeffrey got his start in New York politics,
担任市长约翰•林赛的幕僚
working in the office of Mayor John Lindsay,
当时大家给他的绰号是“狂小子”
where his affectionate nickname was Squirt.
在派拉蒙电影公司
At Paramount Pictures,
他在迪勒和埃斯纳的阴影下发展
he studied in the shadow of Barry Diller and Michael Eisner.
在那里, 人们给他的外号是“金毛猎犬”
And there his nickname was the Golden Retriever.
在迪斯尼, 他不再有绰号了
At Disney, he really had no nickname,
因为在这里, 他这可以走出他人的阴影
because this was the place where he could step out of the shadows
在好莱坞闯出自己的事业
and make his mark on Hollywood.
在派拉蒙时, 我就注意到他了
I sought him out at Paramount.
共事过程中, 我发现他优秀极了
We'd worked together. He was just fantastic.
他很勤奋, 有担当, 有所执迷
He was a worker. He was committed. He was obsessed.
他擅长交际
He made relationships.
一旦我们发现优秀的人才, 他就会设法进行拉拢
If we found somebody good, he would lasso him into our company.
他在派拉蒙这么做
He did it at Paramount
在迪斯尼也是, 而且做得很好
and he did it at Disney and he did it great.
我一直记得来到迪斯尼的第一天
So I always remember my first day at Disney when I showed up
我走进迈克尔的办公室, 他说
and I went to Michael's office and he said,
“过来, 我给你看点东西”
"Come here, I wanna show you something."
我走过去, 他正看着窗外
And I walked over and he was looking out his window.
从他站的位置
And, you know, from his corner,
他指向窗外的七彩大楼
he pointed down to the Ink and Paint building.
问道 你知道他们在里面做什么吗
He said, "Do you know what they do down there?"
我说 不知道
And I said,"No."
他说 那是他们制作动画电影的地方
He said,"That's where they make the animated movies."
我说 是吗? 他答道 是的
I went,"Really?" He said,"Yes."
他又说 现在这归你管了
And he said,"And that's your problem."
第一次意见分歧发生在一部备受瞩目的电影上
The first culture clash happened on a much-anticipated film
这部电影制作期长, 投资巨大
that was years in the making and millions over budget,
片名为: 黑神锅传奇
The Black Cauldron.
他不知所措, 他上窜下跳
He's overwhelmed. He'd be jumping up and down.
年轻组员很不耐烦, 急于展现他们的点子
The younger guys were really impatient and anxious to show what they could do,
他们觉得保守的老一辈拖了后腿
but they felt like they were being held back by the remnants of the old guard.
而年长的组员则认为
While the older guys thought
这帮小子乳臭未干, 应该安分点
the kids were brats and should get back to work.
黑神锅传奇这部电影, 我们从五本书开始
In the case of The Black Cauldron, we started with five books
把它们浓缩到一本
and had to condense them down into one.
我到岗后的前几个星期
In the first couple of weeks I was at the studio,
观看了黑神锅传奇
I saw The Black Cauldron.
这是部黑暗而棘手的片子
It was a very dark movie and a very troubled movie.
实在是太, 太, 太暴力恐怖了
"This is just way, way, way too violent and too scary.
必须要做一些删减
You have to edit some of these things out."
他们说, 你不能删减动画电影
They said, "Well, you can't edit an animated movie."
我说, 当然可以。而他们说, 不, 不可以的
I said,"Well, of course you can." And they said,"No, you can't."
嘿, 不行, 别这样
Hey. No, you don't.
可能你会觉得我在挑起内部矛盾
Honestly, you would think that I was causing World War Three at the studio,
因为我确实说过, 你们把片子送到剪辑室
because I literally said,"Well, you get the film and bring it to an edit bay
我来教你们如何删减动画片
and I'm gonna show you how you edit an animated movie."
我认真的
I mean it.
杰弗里亲力亲为, 强硬霸道
Jeffrey was hands-on, elbows-on, sharp elbows-on.
你永远猜不透他的喜怒
You never knew if he was gonna hug you or kick you.
一次接受采访时, 他说道
He said in an interview around that time,
我们要唤醒睡美人
"We've got to wake up Sleeping Beauty."
黑魔神的制片人乔•黑尔听后很生气
Then Joe Hale, the producer of The Black Cauldron, was furious.
他们以为自己是谁?他说, 睡美人明明已经醒了
"Who are these guys?"He said. "Sleeping Beauty is awake."
不久后, 他被炒了
He was fired not long after.
黑魔神耗资4400万美元
Black Cauldron cost $44 million to make
票房收入却只及投资一半
and made less than half that at the box office.
更加耻辱和伤人的是
And, to add insult to injury,
它的票房还不如爱心熊的电影
it was beat out at the box office by The Care Bears Movie.
那一刻, 迪斯尼动画发展跌入谷底
That day, Disney Animation hit bottom.
又见到罗恩•克莱门茨了
This is Ron Clements again.
讲讲贝克街的巴兹尔这部电影吧
Explain a little bit about Basil of Baker Street.
这部电影讲了一只老鼠的故事
Well, Basil of Baker Street is about a little mouse
他有点像福尔摩斯
that is just like Sherlock Holmes.
刚开始罗伊给我们安排了一项任务
One of the first things Roy did was he arranged one day
就是浏览整个电影的故事板
for us to be pitched the storyboards for the entire movie.
好像动画片就应该这么做
It's like going back to what animation really is supposed to be.
那三个小时时间里
And for the better part of three hours,
我们一张张看完了整部电影的故事板
literally the entire movie was pitched to us.
你看完一张, 接着看下一张
You go through one storyboard, then they bring another
坐在那好几个小时
and you'd sit there for hours and--
我都不记得第一张故事板的内容
I couldn't remember what was in the first storyboard.
这对我来说有些困难
It was a very hard process for me to deal with.
因为我主要负责的是剧本方面
I'd been used to dealing in the script area.
我们看完后, 都如释重负, 说道
So when it was over, we all sort of said,
非常感谢, 做得好
"Thanks very much," And,"Great job."
迈克尔说, 跟我一起回办公室
And Michael said, "Walk back to my office with me."
我们往回, 走到办公室
So we walked back. On the way back to the office,
他问, 你觉得怎么样?我说, 不知道
he said,"What do you think?" I said,"L have no idea."
他说, 我也是
And he said,"Neither do I."
我说, 这样吧
I said,"Well, here's the thing.
我们有175名员工
We have 175 people and
我们每天付给他们工钱
we're paying them every day to come to work.
工资反正是要发的
And we're gonna pay them
无论他们做不做这片子
whether they make this movie or they don't make this movie,
所以我们还是做比较好
so I guess we probably ought to make the movie."
然后他说, 我也是这么想的
And he says to me, "Well, that's exactly my feeling too."
真人电影发展很快, 杰弗里需要更多办公场地
The live-action business was booming and Jeffrey needed offices
给他的新晋明星
for his new stable of stars,
比如贝蒂•米德勒和罗宾•威廉姆斯
like Bette Midler and Robin Williams.
他决定占用动画部的办公楼
He wanted the animation building.
消息从动画部头儿罗伊•迪斯尼处传下来
The news came down from the head of animation, Roy Disney,
他通知动画部的员工
announcing that the animators would have
必须搬出该办公楼
to move out of the building and off the lot.
这到底怎么回事?
What was going on here? I mean,
要知道这栋楼
this was the building where
可是沃特•迪斯尼制作灰姑娘和小飞侠的地方
Walt Disney made Cinderella and Peter Pan,
就这样腾出来给别人?
and we were having to vacate?
整个决定只能参考一份备忘录
All there was was this memo.
没有会议, 没有辩论, 只有一份备忘录
There was no meeting, no debate, just a memo.
貌似罗伊也不想做过多解释
I guess Roy didn't want the confrontation.
离开那天, 两百名不安的员工
On our last day, 200 frightened people,
昔日辉煌的迪斯尼动画工作室的残兵剩将
the remnants of Disney's once great Animation Studio,
聚集在老动画部大楼前
gathered on the steps of the old Animation building
留下最后一张合影
for one last photo before we left.
之后我们搬到了新办公楼
So to carry that forward into the new building,
坐落于格兰岱尔市, 选址马马虎虎
which was in Glendale, not a great area,
建筑就基本上是一些简陋可怜的房子
but the building itself was such a gutted wretch of a building,
用空心砖砌起来
with just cinder block
铺着破烂的地毯, 外围有铁丝网
and torn-up carpet and barbed wire around it
肮脏的小车库满是碎酒瓶子
and broken bottles on the crummy little parking lot.
爱德, 这几天都在忙什么?
So, Ed, what are you doing nowadays?
我就对着桌子发发呆
I'm just emotionally under my desk.
我们都认定一周之内就要卷铺盖走人
Well, we were all pretty sure that we'd be fired in a week or so,
所以决定为迪斯尼动画来一次特别的庆祝
so we decided to celebrate the apparent end of Disney Animation
那就是全景再现电影现代启示录
with a full-scale reenactment of Apocalypse Now.
我们没有长长的黑走廊了, 现在都是小隔间
We don't have long dark hallways anymore. We got cubicles.
办公区采用了开放的设计, 你无处躲藏
The warehouse was an open plan, so you couldn't really hide.
大家随时可以进行即兴的交流
It opened the place to frequent and spontaneous communications
无论是在过道, 还是洗手间
in the hallways, in the men's room.
来吧, 过来
Come on in. Come on.
很多从此屏障被打破了
The barriers were down.
搬迁后, 杰弗里召集全体动画师开会
After the move, Jeffrey called a meeting of all the animators,
大家可以发问和表达意见
so the crew could air their questions and concerns.
杰弗里站起来, 说: 拿出你们最尖锐的问题
So Jeffrey got up and said, "Give me your best shot.
别给我留面子
Hit me in the solar plexus.
随便问, 我脸皮厚得很
Ask me anything. I've got rhino skin."
有人便问道
And somebody piped up and said,
你简直不知道自己在做什么
"We don't think you know what you're doing."
我回答到: 听着, 我就在这, 哪儿也不去
And I said, "Look, I'm here. I'm not going away.
而且我很乐意
And I'm more than happy to
与你们相处, 向你们学习
learn and take the time and be educated by you.
但没办法, 我们最近的几部动画片
The fact is that the last couple of animated movies made
都做得不尽如人意
were not particularly good."
动画部会议开得很频繁
The animation meetings were usually scheduled,
不仅频繁, 而且时间是早上6点
a lot of times, at 6:00 in the morning.
所以, 我还记得早起开车去开会的情形
And so, yeah, I remember driving to go to those meetings.
会场气氛通常有些奇怪
And then that sort of strange atmosphere at that time of the morning,
大家都一副睡眼惺忪的样子
and hardly anyone is awake or around.
后来他开始召集大家周日早上8点开会
He began calling meetings for 8:00 in the morning on Sunday.
记得第二次参加的时候, 我受不了了
And I think it was about the second one, I was just angry.
因为这简直是一种人格侮辱
Because it's just such a total sign of disrespect
把一群才华横溢的员工当苦力使唤
for a lot of very talented people who are working their ass off for you.
所以我说, 杰弗里, 我们得改个时间开会
And I said,"Jeffrey, we gotta have these meetings at some other time,
我跟你说, 如果你再弄这么早
because I promise you, if you have another one of these things at 8 a.M.,
我就穿着睡衣过来
I'm showing up in my pajamas."
您感到骄傲吗, 迪斯尼先生?
Aren't you proud of it, Mr. Disney?
何止骄傲, 我简直要膨胀了
Why, I'm so proud, I think I'll bust.
时间差不多是…
I think it was right around the time of--
奥斯卡颁奖那会儿… 就是那个时候
The Oscars were-- It was just around the corner.
他说, 我对奥斯卡奖不感兴趣
And he said,"You know, I'm not interested in the Academy Awards.
我只对钱感兴趣
I'm interested in the Bank of America awards," You know.
我只在乎能赚多少钱
"What the money these things pull in."
他这个观点
And it was just absolutely
是艺术工作者们最反感的
the worst thing to tell a room full of artists.
这令他们大失所望
It was so discouraging.
一天, 杰弗里对我说
Jeffrey, one day, he said to me,
你需要找个副手了
"You really need to get your own Jeffrey Katzenberg."
我想了想说, 没错
And I began thinking and thinking, "You know, it's right.
我不能总是亲历亲为, 毕竟能力也有限
I can't do this by myself and I'm not that talented anyway."
所以我打电话给鲍勃•弗里兹帕特里克
So the call I made was to Bob Fitzpatrick,
他当时正在参加奥林匹克艺术节
who was in the Olympic Arts Festival at the time.
他说, 我有人选了, 我让他去找你
He says,"I think I have somebody. I'll send him over to you.
这个人叫彼得•施耐德
His name is Peter Schneider."
当时我和妻子女儿住在小小的公寓里
I was living in a small apartment with my wife and baby daughter,
她老催我说, 去找份工作吧
and she said to me, "Go get a job," You know.
我当时很天真, 没有思想包袱, 没有定势思维
I was naive. I had no baggage, no preconceived notions.
也不在乎过去发生了些什么
I didn't care what had been done in the past.
但我知道, 我的水平肯定强过黑神锅传奇
I knew that I could do no worse than The Black Cauldron.
反正我也是光脚不怕穿鞋, 无所顾忌
You know, you can't fall off the first floor.
彼得担任的职位是动画部副总
Peter was given the title of vice president,
看不惯他的动画师们, 将他比作电影里的不合群者
which, to the insurgent population of animators, made him the Man.
而对抗这个不合群者的办法, 就是讽刺漫画
And the main weapon to fight the Man was the dreaded caricature.
彼得是个很可怕的家伙, 真的
Well, Peter was kind of a scary thing, you know.
精瘦的身材, 高高的个子
A small frame, wiry, and, you know,
神经兮兮的, 给人感觉, 怪怪的
full of nervous energy. He was like,"Nyah."
他看上去像个15岁的孩子
He looked like he was about 15 years old.
脸上总挂着很招嘲讽的笑容
He had this perpetual smile that everybody caricatured.
他睁圆的眼睛和诡异的笑容, 让人背脊发凉
It was like this kind of wide-eyed, predatory smile that really worried people.
每当你走进他办公室
You'd go into his office,
他扭曲的坐姿俨然像一团椒盐卷饼, 特诡异
he would just sit all twisted up like a pretzel. It was odd.
你进门后, 他会按下一个小开关, 把门关上
And he had a little button that closed the door behind you when you went in.
门关上后, 你会不由自主地回头看
When the door closed, you'd kind of look back
好像能从门上发现什么挠痕似的
and see if there were scratch marks on it or something like that.
来到动画部后, 我知道我有100天时间
When I got to Animation, I knew I had a hundred days
来改变这里的文化, 否则我就会被同化
to change the culture before it changed me.
我试着给大家更多自主性
I was trying to empower people,
让他们更加自信, 更重视自己的工作
to make them feel good about themselves, to value the work.
我招进了一些做戏剧时的旧部
I brought in some of my own people who'd worked for me in theater.
凯斯琳•嘉文, 毛琳•邓丽, 汤姆•舒马赫
Kathleen Gavin, Maureen Donley, Tom Schumacher.
甜面包, 我要吃
Sticky buns. Sticky buns.
我邀请了湖人队教练帕特•莱利
I brought in Lakers coach Pat Riley
请他做关于胜利和团队合作的演讲
to talk about winning and teamwork.
彼得要求将每道工序明确细化
Peter picked apart every piece of the production process.
为什么我们上班要打卡?为什么自己做颜料
Why are we punching time clocks? Why are we making our own paint?
为什么不买新的定位尺
Why can't we update our animation pegs?
为什么不多买几部电脑?
Why don't we have more computers?
培训做得怎么样
What about training?
这给人感觉就像光速奔驰的火车
It had this feeling of a freight train leaving the station at light speed.
你要么快点上车, 要么赶紧跳下
You better jump on or jump off fast.
多数人选择了上车, 开始一段疯狂刺激的旅程
Most people got on and it was a wild ride, an exciting time.
这是一种团队体育的精神
There was this team-sport mentality.
只有大家都火力全开, 你才有发挥余地
You can't play the game unless everybody is firing off on all cylinders.
即便是替补队员
Even second string,
也个个摩拳擦掌, 跃跃欲试
you were hungry to be part of this, to jump into the game.
在那种开放包容的气氛下, 大家对一切都精益求精
There was an openness, a permission, almost, to be critical about anything.
当然市场部的人除外
Anything but the Marketing Department.
市场部认为, 贝克街的巴兹尔这个片名
Marketing thought that the title Basil of Baker Street
实在让人摸不着头脑, 应该改一下
was a real head-scratcher and they wanted to change it.
因此彼得发出一份备忘录
So Peter sent off a memo
宣布将片名改为
announcing that they were changing the title to:
老鼠神探（或妙妙探）
The Great Mouse Detective.
此举招来反对声一片, 而且我们开始
The resistance was pretty fierce and we all started trying things
按照自己的方法行事, 但都无济于事
to get it to be our way and it wasn't gonna change.
一名画师想到个好主意,
One of the artists got the bright idea
他以彼得的名义伪造了份备忘录
to send out a fake memo, in Peter's name,
宣称现在所有的迪斯尼影片都要改名
saying that now all the Disney films will be renamed.
从今以后, 白雪公主
From now on, Snow White
将改为七个矮人慷慨助姑娘
would become Seven Little Men Help a Girl.
而匹诺曹将改名为木头男孩下凡间
And Pinocchio would be The Wooden Boy Who Became Real.
彼得明白这场玩笑是在挑战他的权威
Peter saw the joke memo as undermining his authority
他要求彻查恶作剧始作俑者
and demanded to know who wrote the memo.
画师们觉得这点子很有趣, 都不愿供出作者
The artists saw it as good clean fun and kept the author a secret.
相反, 他们把这事捅到杰弗里那儿, 想再作弄一番
They even sent it up to Jeffrey's office for added amusement.
有人放了彼得汽车轮胎的气
Peter, I think his tires were slashed
或是有人砸了他的汽车玻璃
or somebody busted his window in his car in the lot.
有些人则表现得很理性
Some, you know, really mature way to handle the situation.
彼得把大家召集到放映室
Peter came in and put us all in the screening room
把我们结实地教训了一顿
and just tore us a new one.
他暴起青筋的样子活像个漫画人物
That was the fabled triple-veiner that Peter had,
我是说, 他简直
where, I mean, he was, like,
暴跳如雷, 怒火四射, 真的非常生气
levitating and glowing, he was so mad.
那次会议后, 我们都有点尊敬他了
I think after that meeting, we all kind of respected him.
很难得的是, 他没有说
What I love is he didn't say,
给我闭嘴, 看我不惯, 就给我滚
"Shut up. If you don't like it, there's the gate."
他说的是, 我们要做伟大的电影
He said, "We're gonna make great films."
杰弗里一笑置之, 说道
And Jeffrey just laughed it off and said,
那当然了
"Don't even worry about it."
我与杰弗里的关系因此拉近了, 虽然有些奇怪
And I think that cemented my relationship with Jeffrey, in some weird way,
而且, 与动画师们的关系也好转了
and also cemented my relationship with the artists.
意想不到的是, 这次事件被某电视节目开发为一类题型
And as a bonus, the memo even ended up as a category on Jeopardy!
最后, 是同义词题
And finally, In Other Words.
这道同义词题, 来自一次小题大做的恶作剧
In Other Words came about as the result of a big foofaraw
去年发生于迪斯尼工作室
that occurred at the Disney Studios last year
当时员工们发动了一次小规模抗议
when the employees staged a minor revolt
因为公司将贝克街的巴兹尔
when they changed the title of Basil of Baker Street
改名为老鼠神探
to The Great Mouse Detective.
我选300分的同义词题
In Other Words for 300.
谜底是“穿透明鞋子的女孩”
"The girl with the see-through shoes."
- 玛娇丽 - 谁是灰姑娘?
Marjorie. Who is Cinderella?
谁是灰姑娘?恭喜答对了
Who is Cinderella? That’s good.
老鼠神探于1986年上映, 好评如潮
The Great Mouse Detective was released in 1986 to good reviews
票房也取得丰收
and respectable box office.
但动画界出现了一个新对手
But there was a new animation threat in town.
史蒂文•斯皮尔伯格
Steven Spielberg.
史蒂文钟爱迪斯尼动画
Steven loved the films of Walt Disney,
所以他也跳进了这一行
so he jumped into the game,
而他的合作者恰恰是唐•布鲁斯
teaming up with none other than Don Bluth,
就是那个在公司低谷期选择背叛的家伙
the animator who kicked us when we were down.
那年, 他制作的美国鼠谭
That year, An American Tail quickly became
迅速成为史上第一部非迪斯尼出品动画票房冠军
the highest-grossing non-Disney animated feature ever,
甩开老鼠神探2200万的票房
beating out The Great Mouse Detective by over $22 million.
奥丽华～
Oliver--
有点意思
That's funny.
我刚来的时候, 奥丽华历险记正在制作中
When I first got there, Oliver and Company was being made.
该片有两名导演
It had two directors.
这是里克•里奇
This is Rick Rich.
这是乔治•斯克里布纳
This is George Scribner.
我炒了里克•里奇
I fired Rick Rich,
他老跟我对着干
who was belligerent to me,
留下了乔治•斯克里布纳, 他对我言听计从
and kept George Scribner, who sucked up to me.
在当时看来, 这么做完全正确
It seemed like the right decision at the time.
毕竟, 顺我者昌
People who like you get ahead.
彼得将他的戏剧背景引入到动画制作
Peter brought his theatrical background to the animation business.
他要求动画师们根据自己的才能选择团队
He demanded that filmmakers pick their own teams based on talent
以及自己的搭档
and who they wanted to work with,
而没有搞什么制度化的论资排辈
not on some form of institutional seniority.
如果你没什么鲜明特点, 就意味着淘汰出局
If you didn't have a strong point of view, you disappeared.
在创意辩论会上, 你必须设法推销你的点子
There was creative debate. You had to defend your ideas.
这意味着更多的图纸
It meant that more drawings
会进入垃圾桶, 而非大荧幕
went into the trash than went up on the screen.
报废的图纸, 我们抛弃的画作
Throwaway drawings. The drawings we just throw away
没有任何意义
that don't mean anything.
这些都是未被采纳的作品
These are the ones that we didn't even use.
无尽的修改, 编剧每改一句台词
Revisions. Every line a writer changed,
就有100幅原画要进垃圾桶
由于公司仍然打着迪斯尼的名号
And because the family name is still the franchise,
所以一直在制作迪斯尼式的长篇动画
the company still produces a few of those Disney animated features,
即使这些动画片耗资巨大
even though they cost a fortune to create.
新片是动画版的雾都孤儿
The new one is an animated version of Oliver Twist,
由比利•乔和贝蒂配音
with Billy Joel and Bette
米德勒负责歌唱和犬吠的部分
Midler doing the singing and barking and growling.
全片接近50万帧
But the finished film may well require a half-million frames,
都是画师们一笔一笔创作而来
each one drawn by an artist
总投资超过1000万美元
at a total cost of more than $10 million,
段时间很难收回成本
more than it can make back anytime soon.
您是否真的可以承受
Can you really afford
做您自己想做的动画?
to do what you wanna do in animation as much as you wanna do?
当然承受不了, 但我们义无反顾
The answer is no, but we're doing it anyway.
- 我们必须这么做 - 必须?
We have to do it in this company. Have to?
没错, 这是我们的光荣传统
We have to. That is our legacy.
在动画领域, 我是说长篇动画
The animation area, the full-length animation,
您承诺过每年出产一部片子, 是这样吗?
you have made a promise to do one film a year. Is that it?
- 这是罗伊承诺的, 我… - 我们一起承诺的
- Well, Roy made it, so I'm-- - We jointly made that one.
没错, 我们确实打算每年出一部
Yeah, it's our intent to make a new one every year.
奥丽华历险记将是计划的第一部
Oliver will be the first in that group.
按照计划, 明年还会推出小美人鱼
And Little Mermaid, the following year, is on schedule to be released a year from now.
我们自信能够做到
And we think we can do it.
我们聚集了越来越多的优秀艺术家
We're accumulating more and more and better artists
也积累了越来越多的经验
and certainly more and more experience as we go.
如虎添翼的是, 一种叫VCR的机器面世了
Helping to feed the coffers in a big way was a machine called the VCR
从此用户可以在自家客厅播放磁带中电影
that could actually play movies from a cassette tape in your own living room.
匹诺曹的录像带
The releasing of Pinocchio in video,
迪斯尼真是令人意外
Disney was never gonna do that.
我还以为他们会顽固不化
I thought that was carved in granite that
过上几年才发布录像带
they would be held in storage for seven years and then released carefully.
到底什么促使他们发布录像带呢?
How was the decision made to put them out in video?
我不认为做这个决定有什么困难的
I don't think there's been any more careful decision than we have reached.
目前我们只推出了一部经典: 匹诺曹
And we have reached it so far only in respect to the one classic, Pinocchio.
今年夏天上市了, 市场反响很好
It's out now this summer. It's doing very well.
这以后我们会慢慢决定是否推出其它经典作品
It's only after that that we'll slowly decide what to do with the rest of it.
毕竟录像带版的匹诺曹
And after all, a video release this summer hardly is gonna affect Pinocchio
对七年前制作的戏剧版几乎没有影响
when it's released theatrically another seven years from now.
匹诺曹作为试金石, 取得了巨大成功
Pinocchio went out as a trial balloon and made millions.
它就像印钞机一样,
It was like a license to print money,
因为重制经典作品几乎没有成本
since there were no costs for the old titles.
很快其它经典作品也被制作成录像带发售
But that immediately upped the ante to get more titles into the pipeline.
为了发掘新题材
So to find these new titles,
任何人, 无论是艺术家, 文秘还是清洁工
anybody, artists, secretaries, janitors,
都可以在铜锣秀上提出他们的见解
could come in and pitch their ideas in a gong show.
有些创意, 如风中奇缘
Some ideas, like Pocahontas,
就是由一张原画和一个片名逐步完成的
were green-lit from a single drawing and a title.
其它的, 如小美人鱼, 刚开始被否决了
Others, like Little Mermaid, were gonged at first,
因为与前作美人鱼太相似, 但后来又获通过
because it was too much like Splash, but came back later.
当时很多项目都获准开工
And there were all sorts of projects being green-lit.
其中一部续集作品叫救难小英雄, 以澳大利亚为故事背景
A sequel idea called Rescuers Down Under, set in Australia.
还有王子与乞儿, 米老鼠也在片中出现
Prince And The Pauper, starring Mickey Mouse.
还有一些沃特•迪斯尼曾经构思的项目
And an old shelved project that Walt Disney himself considered back in the 1940s,
比如美女与野兽
Beauty and the Beast.
除了已故的迪斯尼先生
Not only does the ghost of Walt Disney,
当时的制作组也出现创意井喷
the creative genius, keep Eisner awake at night.
埃斯纳初到公司时
When he first came to the company,
他发现高管们决策前, 会习惯性地问一句
he discovered that executives routinely made decisions by asking,
若是沃特, 他会怎么做?
"What would Walt have done?"
通常, 有些人会斩钉截铁地说
To a certain extent, people, somebody, would surely have said,
沃特应该不会这么做
"Walt probably wouldn't have done that."
我们要打破这样的循环
We needed to break that cycle
我们要将思维打开
and we needed to get out into the whole town.
有人说, 我们活在死人的阴影下
The argument that says,"Some dead guy is trying to run your operation."
我们不能这样
You can't do that.
迪斯尼先生不是金科玉律
I don't think Disney is like the constitution.
我们没有必要墨守成规
I don't think we have to preserve it and put it in glass.
公司还在成长 不思进取意味着坐以待毙
I think it's a growing-- And if it's not growing, it's gonna die.
迪斯尼是一个伟大名字
Our name is a fantastic asset
它来自于一个充满创新精神的伟人
and it represents a terrific man who was very creative.
我不想成为那个自砸招牌的人
And I'd hate to be the person who shot himself in the foot and ended it.
我不愿坐吃空山, 我要继往开来
I don't wanna leave that legacy. I'd like to keep it going.
我希望有所建树, 带来新的东西
But I'd like to add to it. I'd like to have new things.
你最害怕什么?
What do you worry about?
搬石头砸自己的脚
Shooting myself in the foot.
1983年来, 迪斯尼净利润翻了三倍
Disney's net profits tripled since 1983
股价涨了五倍
and the stock price is up five-fold.
迪斯尼人很自豪地自称为米老鼠公司
Disney people are proud to call themselves a Mickey Mouse operation.
多数分析师认为, 迪斯尼能再创辉煌
According to most analysts, the magic returned with
得益于弗兰克•威尔斯和迈克尔•埃斯纳的带领
the appointment of Frank Wells as president of the company and Michael Eisner as chairman.
在埃斯纳和威尔斯的掌管下
Under Eisner and Wells,
电影部试金石影业蓬勃发展
the new Touchstone Movie Division became a production powerhouse,
制作了如贝弗丽山奇遇记
turning out such hits as Down and Out in Beverly Hills,
残酷之人, 金钱本色等佳片
Ruthless People, The Color of Money,
以及新兴电影人才成长的摇篮
and what amounts to a farm club for feature filmmakers,
迪斯尼周日电影秀
The Disney Sunday Movie.
1987年迪斯尼与迈克尔•杰克逊合作的伊奥船长上演
与乔治•卢卡斯合作的星际之旅也正式开启
and the Disney George Lucas collaborative adventure, Star Tours.
真人电影, 主题公园以及商品行业都如火如荼
The live-action movies, the parks, the merchandise were all on fire,
而动画片
but Animation,
仍然像是被冷落的孩子
well, we still seemed like a stepchild.
不得不说, 我对前路感到担忧
And I gotta say, I was very nervous about where we were heading,
不知道迪斯尼的未来在哪里
where was the future of Disney going.
它像一辆疯狂行驶的汽车
It seemed to be being driven by a maniac at the wheel,
因为有杰弗里这样猛踩油门的掌舵人
in terms of Jeffrey, with his heavy foot on the accelerator,
在拥挤的城市飞速奔驰
driving full speed in a very crowded city.
开始
Action.
当时有个老项目叫谁陷害了兔子罗杰
An old development project called Who Framed Roger Rabbit
因为斯皮尔伯格的青睐而进展神速
shifted into hyper-drive when Steven Spielberg became interested.
要知道, 沃特•迪斯尼的电影对我影响极大
You know, I have been influenced profoundly by the films of Walt Disney,
特别是30, 40直到50年代的片子
especially the films from the '30s, '40s and right through the '50s.
我真心觉得这部电影就是在向沃特致敬
And I really feel that this is a movie that we're making for Walt.
电影回到未来的导演罗伯特•泽米基斯
Back to the Future director Robert Zemeckis
受命执导兔子罗杰
was signed to direct Roger Rabbit.
泽米基斯和斯皮尔伯格包办了影片的创意部分
Bob and Steven made up the creative team on the film,
而杰弗里负责掐紧预算
while Jeffrey watched the purse strings.
我们希望联合迪斯尼的技术
We always wanted the Disney technique,
迪斯尼的美工
the beautiful Disney animation,
华纳兄弟的人物塑造
the great Warner Bros. Characterization.
以及泰克斯•艾弗利的幽默
And Tex Avery humor.
这样的组合简直屌炸天
You know, dynamite-down-your-pants type stuff.
兔子好像… 不想回去而霍斯金斯…
And the rabbit's like-- Doesn't wanna go back in and Hoskins...
要凑成上述的梦幻组合
It was a trifecta of elements
泽米基斯知道不能指望迪斯尼动画部
that Bob knew he couldn't get from the Disney Animation Department,
因此他通过动画界元老理查德•威廉姆斯
so he turned to animation veteran Richard Williams
将拍摄点定在伦敦
to animate the movie in London,
接着彼得派我监督动画的制作
and Peter sent me to London to ride herd on the animation.
这对伯班克的那帮人打击很大
It was a real stomach punch for the guys back in Burbank,
而实际上, 当时没什么人关注迪斯尼动画部
but the truth was nobody really thought much of Disney Animation back then.
斯皮尔伯格, 泽米基斯和威廉姆斯的组合充满了魔力
The combination of Spielberg, Zemeckis and Dick Williams was like a talent magnet
全世界动画人蜂拥而至, 欲加盟该项目
and animators from all over the world just flocked to the project.
因此伦敦形成了伯班克之外一个分部
So now there was a unit in Burbank and one in London.
彼得往返两地, 频繁地施展激将法
And Peter would travel back and forth to rattle everybody's cage.
在伦敦工作室
When he was in London,
他就说伯班克的小美人鱼项目做得多出色
he'd say how great the guys in Burbank were doing on The Little Mermaid.
在伯班克
Then back in Burbank,
他就大肆赞扬兔子罗杰有多棒
he'd brag about how great the guys on Roger Rabbit were doing.
没人试过这样做电影
Nobody had attempted a movie like this before,
预算也直线攀升
and the budget just soared.
因此杰弗里心急火燎地把我们招到纽约
It got so heated that Jeffrey summoned us all to New York
告诉我们实在一个子儿也拿不出了
to tell us that we did not have one more dime to spend on this movie.
真没钱了
No more money.
然后我们乘着豪车或直升机赶往机场, 直飞伦敦
Then we all took limos, helicopters to the airport to fly Concorde back to London.
我们铺张地办这次会议, 来告诉大家我们没钱了
He spent all this money on a meeting to tell us we had no money.
一钱难死英雄汉, 典型的好莱坞游戏
It was a very Hollywood moment.
公司本部, 杰弗里因迈克尔给的资金压力而郁闷
Back home, Jeffrey was getting beat up by Michael about the costs.
创意人员完全被预算捆缚了手脚
We just had to put a financial box around all this creativity.
但如果不控制预算, 局面就会难以收拾
And without that, the end result would have been complete chaos.
这让我和迈克尔之间产生了很多摩擦和问题
It created a tremendous amount of friction and difficulty between Michael and I,
不是他不相信这部电影, 他很有信心
not because he didn't believe in the movie. He did.
只是因为它实在太昂贵了
Financially it just became so expensive.
加上迈克尔又是个很保守的人
And Michael, who is fundamentally conservative,
他对如此冒险的行为感到很不快
just got very, very uncomfortable with it.
停, 再来一遍
Cut. Let's do it again.
而我也无法掌控局面
And I was unable to control it.
谁陷害了兔子罗杰
Who Framed Roger Rabbit
是一部好莱坞不可多得的惊喜制作
is one of those home runs that Hollywood hits every once in a while.
可以比肩2001太空漫游和第三类接触, 很像ET外星人
It's a movie like 2001 or Close Encounters or especially like E. T.
它有很多技术创新
that's a technical breakthrough
同时又充满了趣味
and a lot of fun both at the same time.
兔子罗杰引发热议
Roger Rabbit made headlines
夺得奥斯卡奖 还让公司赚得盆满钵满
and won Oscars for technical innovation and returned just millions to the studio.
兔子罗杰的核心主创人员回到伯班克
The top talent on Roger was shipped back to Burbank
开始投入到奥丽华历险记和小美人鱼的制作
and put to work on Oliver and Company and Little Mermaid.
年轻国际化人才的创意爆发
It was like an injection of fresh, young, international talent
简直是可遇不可求
that would pay dividends for years to come.
六个月后, 奥丽华历险记
Six months later, Oliver and Company opened
与斯皮尔伯格的史前大陆同期上映
on the same day as Spielberg's Land Before Time.
来吧, 我们吃了他！
Come on. Let's eat him!
差不多三四个月后
Well, by the end of the three or four months,
我们赚了5500万的样子
we'd made 55, 56, 54.
而且我们打败了史前大陆, 感觉…
And we beat Land Before Time and it was like--
很多人觉得说, 嘿, 有料有料
I think a lot of people were like, "Hey, there's something--
这电影有看头
There's something here."
迈克尔与公司整体的磨合期逐渐渡过
The chaos that Roy ushered in when he hired Michael was starting to pay off
突然间, 大家都变得非常团结协作
and suddenly everybody was happy to be associated with Toontown.
这是第一部童话…
This is the first fairy tale that…
在来一遍, 过去三十年间, 这么多经典
Take two. In the last 30 years, three decades.
为什么选择了美人鱼?
Why was Mermaid chosen?
这个嘛, 有一天我们一起去吃午饭
Well, I mean, it was chosen because we all went to a lunch
差不多是三四年前, 我们大家一起
about three or four years ago and all of us--
其实这有点试验的意思
It was sort of a development-type thing.
我们每个人想出三个点子
And we were supposed to come in with our three ideas.
不知道是否会被采用
I don't know if you can use any of this,
但这种做法
but this is sort of more the truth than,
比自己藏着掖着好多了
you know, what we may wind up saying later.
这样做可以看到不同的想法
And basically they wanted to draw on different ideas.
而罗恩提出的一点就是小美人鱼
And one of the ideas that Ron brought in was The Little Mermaid.
这是他的三个点子之一
He had-- That was one of his three.
杰弗里的朋友大卫•格芬
Jeffrey's friend David Geffen
向他推荐了一支作曲团队
called him about a songwriting team,
霍华德•阿斯曼和艾伦•门肯
Howard Ashman and Alan Menken,
格芬曾与他们合作过一部非百老汇舞台剧
that he'd worked with on the off-Broadway hit
恐怖小屋
Little Shop of Horrors.
彼得以前也与他们合作过同一部剧
Peter had worked with them on the same show as company manager,
因此委任他们为小美人鱼作曲
so he brought them in to work on The Little Mermaid.
霍华德当时可谓心灰意懒
Howard was just coming off a terrible disappointment
因为他的音乐剧《微笑》在百老汇遭遇滑铁卢
when his musical Smile crashed and burned on Broadway.
他准备在洛杉矶东山再起
He came to Los Angeles to start over again.
霍华德不是迪斯尼最引人注意的那一个
Howard wasn't exactly the first guy who sprang to mind when you said Disney.
他出生在巴尔的摩的一个犹太家庭
He was born into a Jewish family in Baltimore,
从小就在当地的儿童剧院舞台表演
where he grew up on-stage in the local Children's Theater Association.
他是同性恋, 前卫, 热爱音乐剧, 特别迷彼得•潘
He was gay, edgy, and loved musicals, especially Peter Pan.
当我得到与迪斯尼合作的机会, 我简直跳…
When I was approached with an opportunity to work for Disney, period, I leapt at the--
我告诉自己, 动画也不错
I said,"What about Animation?
就在动画部工作吧
What about working in that department?"
这是我真正想做的
That was what I really wanted to do here,
超过任何其它事物, 任何真人电影
much, much more than anything, really, in live-action.
因为我非常热衷于音乐剧
Because I'm really a musical-theater person
而且我看到了音乐剧与动画片间的紧密关系
and I do see a very, very strong connection between these two media.
起初的剧本里有这么一个角色
We had this character in the original treatment, the script.
是一只螃蟹, 他有些…
It was a crab character that was kind of-- Would be--
他一直照顾着美人鱼
Sort of look after the mermaid
并且帮她解决麻烦, 保护她
and try to keep her out of trouble and watch over her.
他执拗, 老气, 古怪, 典型的国王右大臣
He was kind of a crusty, old, crotchety character The king's right-hand guy.
他工作勤恳, 还是海底世界的指挥家
who worked for the king and was like the conductor in the undersea world.
霍华德说, 把他设定为牙买加人吧
Howard said, "Why not make him Jamaican?"
我们的第一反应是, 牙买加?
And our first reaction was,"Jamaican?"
我们都有些理解不过来
I mean, it was like a total twist on what we were thinking.
他召集所有的鱼和事物
He rounds up all of these fish and all of this stuff
想说服艾丽儿不要变成人
to convince Ariel not to try to become human.
他们想用乐器和他们自身, 为她奉上一场演出
And they more or less put on a show for her by playing all these instruments and themselves.
然后, 音乐开始了
Okay, we hear it start.
他开始为乐曲定调
He starts establishing the rhythm.
蛤蜊和牡蛎登场
The clams pick it up, and oysters,
而他在龙虾身上敲击
and he's beating on lobsters, whatever.
都是打击乐的声音
It's all percussive
来自整个海底世界的节奏
and it's all the undersea world making the percussion.
空气中充满了能量
There was electricity in the air.
我是说, 人们能看到这是真正的天才之作
I mean, there was real genius at work and people knew it.
霍华德, 从营销的角度说
Howard, in a salesmanship way, I think,
他希望处理得更即兴一些
trying to treat it sort of a little more off-the-cuff,
不过我觉得他所有的创作都是突发的灵感
but I think he had written all the songs five minutes after he got the treatment,
比如说, 现在有首歌
but said, "Now, here, say you had a song,
不如就取名“憧憬你们的世界”吧
say it was called 'Part of Your World.'
其实歌名无所谓, 就叫憧憬你们的世界吧
It could be anything, but say it was called 'Part of Your World'."
之后他… 还有艾伦…
And then he had a-- And Alan--
我们聚在霍华德格林威治村的公寓
We were in Howard's apartment in Greenwich Village and it was--
艾伦站出来弹了这首曲子
Alan came over and played it on the piano.
霍华德伴唱, 效果非常好
And Howard sang it right there and it sounded great.
真的要好好拿捏这个度
So really try to work with just the intensity.
就是那种心潮澎湃, 却压抑不发的感觉
It's like it's about all that emotion and then not letting it all out.
- 压抑不发 - 对, 都藏在心里
Not letting it out. Not letting it out, but having it here.
就这样, 真的, 这…
That stuff. Really, it's--
- 我是不是声音大了点? - 你挺好的
Am I still a little too loud? You're great.
- 好点吗? - 你很棒
Better that time? You're great.
但没错, 这里要欢快一些
But you're right, it gets a little bright here.
紧张的程度要超过…
The intensity is better than--
超过正常说话, 超过埃塞尔•摩曼
Is better than noise. Than Ethel Merman, right.
但你唱的不是埃塞尔•摩曼, 这是一种内心的纠结
But you're not doing Ethel Merman. It's inner intensity, though.
几乎所有的音乐剧
In almost every musical ever written,
都有这样的场景, 通常是当晚的第三首歌
there's a place, it's usually the third song of the evening.
有时是第二首或第四首, 总之出现很早
Sometimes it's the second, sometimes it's the fourth, but it's quite early.
女主角通常会坐在什么东西上面
And the leading lady usually sits down on something,
如蓬莱仙舞中的树墩
sometimes it's a tree stump in Brigadoon,
或是窈窕淑女中, 科芬花园的柱子
sometimes it's under the pillars of Covent Garden in My Fair Lady,
或是异形奇花中的垃圾桶
or it's a trash can in Little Shop of Horrors.
总之女主角会坐在什么上面
But the leading lady sits down on something
然后歌唱自己的梦想
and sings about what she wants in life
然后观众就会爱上她
and the audience falls in love with her
这就为后续的故事奠定了基调
and then roots for her to get it for the rest of the night.
听过茱蒂•本森的这首歌后
I heard"Part of Your World," Jodi Benson singing that,
我被深深打动了, 心想, 这活儿我一定要接下
and it just captivated me. I thought, "I have to do that."
我告诉大家, 我来负责画艾丽儿
And I went and told those guys, "I really wanna do Ariel."
他们说: 这个, 不好吧
And they said, "Whoa, I don't know.
这可是个漂亮姑娘, 你确定能画好吗?
This is supposed to be a pretty girl. Can you do that?"
我说: 听着, 我一定要画艾丽儿
I said, "Look, I have to do Ariel.
这是我内心的召唤
I can feel it in my heart."
我们为一群小学生办了场试映
We were previewing for school kids.
然后, 孩子们…
And so the kids--
放映过程中, 一部分内容还未上色
During that screening, a lot of the movie was in black and white.
憧憬你的世界这一段也是, 甚至是素描草稿
Certainly "Part of Your World," A lot of it was in story sketches.
影片开始播放
And the movie comes up on its feet
放到憧憬你的世界这一段时
and we get to "Part of Your World"
观众反应很糟糕
and it's just not connecting.
全场躁动不安
The audience is restless.
我站出来说: 这首歌不行
I came out of that and just said, "Don't think this is working."
所以杰弗里也决定剪掉这一段
So Jeffrey was bound and determined to cut "Part of Your World."
他的意思是: 伙计们, 面对现实吧
It was just like, "Guys, face reality, you know.
这首歌不受欢迎, 不顶用, 放弃吧
It's not working, it's not there. We gotta do something."
我们努力辩护, 但杰弗里听不进
And we pleaded our case. He wouldn't listen to us.
霍华德也在极力坚持
Howard pleaded his case.
他决绝地说
Howard Ashman said,
除非先杀了我, 我死也不会放过你
"Over my dead body. I'll strangle you."
最后格伦•吉恩跟杰弗里说
But finally Glen Keane went to Jeffrey and said,
杰弗里, 别剪这段
"Jeffrey, you cannot cut this.
别犯傻, 这是这部片子的灵魂
You're crazy. This is the heart of the movie.
这是女主人公的梦想
It's her whole dream.
剪掉这段意味着切断观众与人物间的纽带
And to cut that will really gut our emotional involvement with our heroine."
他说服了我, 告诉我这不仅仅是一首歌
He persuaded me that the issue wasn't the song,
而是串联整个故事的主旋律
but other things that were not firing up yet in the sort of rhythm of the movie.
最后证明他是对的
And ultimately he was right.
这一段不仅成为全片亮点
Not only did it stay in the movie,
甚至足以留名影史
but it's one of the more memorable moments in the movie.
童话的城堡如今重放光辉
The sparkle is coming back to Sleeping Beauty's castle.
过去五年, 迪斯尼动画部的团队
Over the last five years, the Disney Animation Department
从150人发展到如今550人的规模
has grown from a low of 150 artists to its current level of nearly 550,
他们坚持传统的制作工艺
doing animation the old-fashioned way,
从素描草稿, 到铅笔测试
from character sketch, to pencil test,
到上色, 最后到放映
to ink and paint, to the screen.
希望小美人鱼能开启
What The Little Mermaid represents, I hope,
动画艺术的复兴
is kind of a renaissance period for the artists themselves.
杰弗里开始发现动画
Jeffrey started discovering Animation
可以展现他的艺术和编辑才华
as a place where he could be artistic, a powerhouse in the editing room,
他也乐意成为影片的发言人
and where he could be the frontman to the press.
杰弗里从中看到了自己的未来
I think he realized something very important to his future.
做得不错, 又有趣
"I'm good at this. This is fun,
而且不用受迈克尔的管教
it's mine and it doesn't include Michael."
小美人鱼的发布会非常成功
The press on Little Mermaid was just spectacular.
票房甚至超过了奥丽华历险记
And the box office, well, was even better than Oliver and Company.
衍生的玩具, 书籍, 拼图和饭盒
And there were loads of toys, books, puzzles and lunch boxes
纷纷推向市场
that just flew off the shelves.
因为动画部的成功
Animation had a big hit on its hands.
公司高层开始关注起来
Jeffrey and Michael started focusing on,
要是多拍几部动画, 公司能多赚一些
"Oh, if we have more titles, it'll be better financially."
而我一直在争取
And I always fought for,
你们能不能投点钱来改进技术?
"Can you take some of those resources and put them back into the business?"
之后我们就买了CAPS
Which was where CAPS came from,
CAPS指的是计算机动画后期处理系统
CAPS being the Computer Animation Postproduction System.
有个叫莱姆•戴维斯的技术员认为
One of the technology guys, Lem Davis,
我们可以用电脑给人物上色
thought we could use computers to paint the characters in our films
并用电脑进行合成
and digitally assemble all the artwork.
这不仅能提高我们的艺术水准
That gives us not only the opportunity to do some really good art,
还让我们有机会探索
but it also gives us the opportunity to really begin to explore
计算机和图形技术的潜力
what these computers and graphics things can do for us
对细节的研究令我们有些着迷
in kind of shorter pieces where we can get really a little crazy.
我也很希望大家努力去探索计算机技术
And I'm looking forward to all of us getting a little crazy.
罗伊向高层申请了一千万购买一套计算机系统
Roy went to Frank Wells with a proposal to spend $10 million
该系统可能不会带来任何回报
on a computer system that might not return a dime,
也可能意味着行业的革命
but would revolutionize the look of our films.
我穿过走廊, 站在弗兰克办公室门口
So I just walked down the hall and stood there in Frank's doorway.
他看着说: 你在这干嘛?
Frank looks up and says, "What are you doing here?"
我说: 我要看着你签下那张支票, 弗兰克
And I said,"I'm just here to make sure you sign that check, Frank."
支票交到了匠白光手中
Frank's check was handed to Alvy Ray Smith,
他是一家小型图形技术公司的联合创始人
the co-founder of a small computer-graphics firm
该公司专注于人物动画
that experimented with character animation
曾经为李施德林漱口水制作过广告片
and made Listerine commercials on the side to make ends meet.
这家公司, 就是皮克斯
It was called Pixar.
CAPS系统应用在救难小英雄的制作
The CAPS computer was thrown into production on Rescuers Down Under.
这是一个方兴未艾的领域
It was unchartered territory.
迪斯尼和皮克斯的员工
The crew from Disney and Pixar
昼夜赶工, 废寝忘食
worked around the clock, sleeping on pallets,
用简陋的办法维护设备
nursing those computers with duct tape and chewing gum,
时间和资金一直十分紧张
and the deadlines and quotas never stopped.
不, 我的想法会吓到你
No, you don't want to hear my thoughts.
你还是别听了
You don't want to hear my thoughts.
那是一段令人沮丧的经历
What I remember most of that period was feeling so brokenhearted
我们试图用CAPS系统完成一部长篇动画
that we had attempted to make a feature film using the CAPS system
而其他公司连短片都还做不了
before anyone had even made a short with it.
我们公布电影发售日前, 从未测试过这套系统
We had never tested the system before we committed to a release date to make a movie.
记得那是凌晨三点
And it's 3:00 in the morning.
彼得走过来, 看了我一眼, 又走开了
Peter Schneider walks in and looks over at me and goes,
怎么样?管用吗?
"Well, is it working yet? Is it working yet?"
真是, 真别给我这么多压力
And it's like, "Oh, I don't need this pressure."
我的首部影片, 救难小英雄上映了
My first film, Rescuers Down Under, came out.
早上八点, 电话响了 - 麦克吗?- 是 - 我是杰弗里
Phone rings at like 8 in the morning. "Mike?""Yeah.""Jeffrey."
怎么样?票房如何?
"Yeah. So, what's going on? What's the numbers?"
他说: 卖了500万, 我们失败了
He said, "Made 5 million. It's over."
什么, 你说什么?
"Well, excuse me, what?"
玩完了, 别惦记了, 继续加油吧
"It's over. Forget it. Move on."
杰弗里撤掉了所有的电视广告
Jeffrey pulled all the TV advertising.
我跟他说: 杰弗里, 你干嘛撤掉广告?
And I said, "Jeffrey, I just can't believe that. You've pulled it?
不打广告了?搞什么?
There's no advertising, nothing?"
他说: 汤姆, 这部电影失败了, 都玩完了
And he said, "Tom, the movie just doesn't work. It's over."
我对着电话哭了起来
And I started to cry on the telephone.
接着他说: 没关系
And then he said, "It's okay.
我们从头来过, 再拍一部
We're gonna move forward and we'll do something else.
你没事吧?
Are you okay?"
我说: 没事
I said, "I'm all right."
他说: 很好, 我们明天开始拍新片
He goes, "Okay, we'll start again tomorrow."
然后他挂掉了电话
And then he hung up the phone.
救难小英雄堪称好莱坞第一部数字电影
Rescuers was the very first digital movie produced in Hollywood.
它为后来者的成功奠定了基础
And without it we would never have achieved what would come later.
下一部电影是美女与野兽
Beauty and the Beast was up next
预算和制作期都变得苛刻许多
and the budget and schedule were cut way, way back.
我们邀请理查德•威廉姆斯执导
We asked Richard Williams to direct the film,
他未答应, 但引荐了他的学生理查德•波德姆
but Williams declined and recommended one of his proteges, Richard Purdum, to direct instead.
波德姆是英国非常成功的广告导演
Purdum was a very successful commercial director based in the U.K.
然后马站起身, 把他托了起来
And then the horse rises up right underneath him.
现在他骑在马后面
Now he's riding on the rear end of the horse,
死死抓住马尾巴
hanging on to the horse's tail,
这时一条狼也抓住马尾, 拼命不放开
and one of the wolves grabs up right onto the tail, yanks the horse,
这时马突然转身, 把人甩了出去
and the horse rears up and throws the guy off
他正好落在狼背上, 像骑马一样
and the guy lands on the back of the wolf, riding on the wolf.
这是我第一次做制片人
It was my first job as producer
希望尽可能做到万无一失
and I wanted to get everything just right.
所以我召集一组人突击改剧本
So I recruited a commando story team of Disney artists
之后我们赶赴伦敦, 做出了无配乐版本
and we moved to London to set to work on a non-musical version of the story.
六个月后, 我们把影片前20分钟放给杰弗里看
After about six months, we took the first 20 minutes of the film to screen for Jeffrey.
我侄女给你答复了吗?
Has my niece given you an answer?
还没呢, 我感觉她只是在耍我
Um, not yet. I think she's playing the coquette with me.
别在意
Forgive her.
作品不算完美, 但最糟糕的结果又能怎样?
It wasn't perfect, but what was the worst that could happen?
总不至于直接枪毙, 推倒重来 那就太疯狂了
They weren't gonna scrap it and start over again. That would be just insane.
我们很不满意, 所以直接毙掉了
It didn't work at all for us, so we literally scrapped it,
样片完全无法接受, 我们决定推倒重来
the first 20 minutes of the movie, and started all over again.
波德姆又继续执导了几个月
Richard Purdum worked for a few more months on Beauty and the Beast,
但当他发现根本无法契合公司要求时
and when it became clear that we would never make his version of the movie,
他选择了辞职
he resigned.
我招聘了两名年轻的分镜师作代理导演
I recruited two young story artists to be the acting directors
并把整个制作组搬回了美国
and moved the entire project back to the warehouses in Burbank.
聚光灯突然打到我和盖里
The spotlight kind of turned on me and Gary,
感觉简直难以置信, 因为…
which struck us as incredibly odd, because--
这种意外感, 就好比你打开厨房灯
The spotlight turned on us like when you turn on the kitchen light
突然照到了地上的蟑螂 惊慌失措下喊道: 什么情况?
and the roaches are on the floor. We were like,"What?"
我们来不及逃, 终究是给逮到了
We didn't get away in time and they caught us.
因此我们就成了美女与野兽的代理导演
So we were made kind of the acting directors of Beauty and the Beast,
说白了, 我们就是片子的导演
which meant-- We had to act like directors.
同时, 在加利福尼亚
Meanwhile, back in California,
杰弗里正开着年度沙滩派对
Jeffrey threw his annual beach party.
嘉宾包括汤姆•克鲁斯, 贝蒂•米勒和罗宾•威廉姆斯
And there was Tom Cruise and Bette Midler and Robin Williams,
大家聚在杰弗里豪宅的沙滩上
all on the beach at Jeffrey's house.
记得霍华德当时也在场
And I remember being there with Howard Ashman,
当时他刚完成小美人鱼,
because after Little Mermaid,
正对新片阿拉丁跃跃欲试
Howard asked to go work on this other thing he was desperate to do for Disney called Aladdin,
恰好同时, 伦敦的美女与野兽项目遭遇困境
at exactly the same time Beauty and the Beast was sort of falling apart in London.
杰弗里强迫霍华德, 也只有他敢这么做
Jeffrey buttonholed Howard, as only he can,
说服他为美女与野兽作曲
and convinced Howard to write the songs for Beauty and the Beast
尽管霍华德并非心甘情愿
even though Howard didn't really want to.
当时老大打电话过来说:
Well, we got a phone call from our boss.
我要介绍你们认识霍华德, 艾伦还有整个创意团队
"We want you to meet with Howard and Alan and the whole creative team
还有美女与野兽将成为一部音乐片
and Beauty and the Beast is gonna become a musical."
我们都跌破了眼镜
We couldn't believe it.
最后我们把办公室设在了一家旅馆
So we ended up setting up shop at the Residence Inn,
在纽约北部, 离霍华德家很近
upstate New York, in Howard's neck of the woods.
我们开始大量的讨论, 抛出各种想法
And we started hashing stuff out and throwing around ideas.
刚开始, 讨论就像学生社团开会一样热闹
Initially it was very, very collegial. It was very upbeat.
我们都觉得很开心
We were having a lot of fun.
但我们遇到了棘手的问题
But one of the things that was a sticking point,
对于影片的开幕, 我们无法达成共识
something that we didn't agree on, was how to open the movie.
霍华德强烈要求电影以动物形态开场
And Howard felt very passionately that the movie should open with a fully animated prologue
展现野兽形态的王子, 而不是小男孩
that showed the Beast in his prince form, except he would be a little boy.
顽皮的小男孩
He'd be a naughty little boy.
而我和盖里, 我们深受怪物一家人中小男孩埃迪的影响
And to Gary and I, we could not get past this Eddie Munster image,
就是那个穿着少爷裤的小毛孩
you know, of this hairy little kid in Little Lord Fauntleroy pants.
而霍华德觉得这很悲伤和不幸
To Howard, it seemed incredibly moving and tragic.
而且他很固执己见, 能言善辩, 有些吓人
He was also very opinionated and very articulate and very intimidating.
所以我们都有些怕他 只好说: 好吧, 按你说的做
And so we were scared of him. It's like, "Okay, we gotta do this."
当时窝着一肚子火的我, 真是很傻很天真
And so, you know, like the stupid, naive, 26-year-old kid that I was,
会议开始, 我说道:
I opened the meeting with,
人形小男孩的开场还是有些轻蔑
"We think that the little Beast boy is kind of a cheap shot."
我想, “轻蔑”这个字眼把霍华德惹毛了
And I think the word "Cheap" Really set Howard off.
他的嘴紧紧抿成一条线
And his mouth was a very tight line
眼睛瞪得很大
and his eyes were getting kind of bigger.
仿佛能看见他头上的乌云
I just saw the clouds darken.
他的脸也阴沉沉的
I just saw his face darken.
一种空前可怕的气场, 仿佛要撕碎我们
And he just ripped into us like I've never been ripped into before.
当时, 根本没人敢为我说话
And no one leapt to my defense, may I just add.
谢谢大家
Thank you very much.
奥斯卡奖得主是:
And the Oscar goes to:
艾伦•门肯, 霍华德•阿斯曼
Alan Menken, Howard Ashman
获奖作品是小美人鱼插曲: 海底世界
for "Under the Sea" From The Little Mermaid.
颁奖礼那晚, 我们两人至少拿了三个奖
Oscar night, we won at least three Oscars between the two of us.
他说: 回到纽约, 我们得好好谈谈
He said, "When we get back to New York, we really have to talk."
他星期一晚上说的这些
And so that was, what, a Monday night.
星期四早上回到纽约
I think he was back by Thursday morning.
我去找他谈话
I came in and he just told me.
我问: 什么事?
I said, you know, "What is it?"
他说: 我以为你知道
And he said, "Well, I guess you know."
我不知道, 我… 他接着说: 我以为你知道
I didn't, or I didn't let myself. He said, "I guess you know.
我得了艾滋病
I'm HlV-positive."
或者是“我有病”之类的
I think, or he maybe said, "I'm sick," Or something.
这真不是我想听到的消息
And I-- It was not what I wanted to hear.
感觉好像少了点什么
It seems like something falls out a little bit there.
是“歌声伴你入眠”这句?
On, "Sing you off to sleep"?
是, 就是这句
Yes. On, "Sing you off to sleep"?
唱的有点重
You're very strong.
这里应该删减下, 以补偿…
Something needs to take off there to compensate for…
我想大卫应该是觉得必须着重一些
Well, I know David had felt that it had to build back in.
你好像说过
I mean, I remember you saying that.
你觉得不应该完全踩着节拍
That you didn't feel you should jump right into tempo.
你是想再加快点?
Do you want it to get faster sooner?
你之前说…
You're asking--
- 他有点带跑节奏了 - 这不是节奏的问题
- He's building into it. - This is not a tempo question.
- 大卫 - 我明你意思
- David - I know what you’re saying.
- 旋律很优雅, 真的很棒 - 好, 那太好了
- The melody, it's neat. It's really pretty. - Oh, good, good.
你不用声嘶力竭地唱这段
So you don't have to scream to get over it.
我们是分轨的, 对吧?
Well, we're separate tracks, aren't we?
没错, 我就怕你没听到提示
True. I just if wonder what you're hearing in your cans--
我们试一遍大声, 一遍小声
Yeah, I'll play it up and play it down.
- 然后看哪个好点 - 好的
- We'll see which is better. - Great.
还有, 这部分也要这么处理
And similarly we should get at least one on this build section.
他对人有着不可思议的影响力
He was an amazing influence on everybody.
我不想拿他跟沃特对比
And I don't want to compare him to Walt,
但不管怎么说
but on the other hand,
他确实有沃特一样强大的影响力
he had that kind of influence on everybody.
美女与野兽完工之前
Before Beauty and the Beast was finished,
我们办了一场大型的演出会
we threw a big dog-and-pony show
邀请了纽约的媒体, 播放了一些电影片段
for the New York press where we showed some clips from the film
艾伦还唱了几首插曲
and Alan sang some of the songs.
我们真的很难想象
I don't think we could have ever imagined
电影和歌曲的受欢迎程度
a more enraptured reception to the movie and the songs.
我们都迫不及待地想与霍华德分享这份喜悦
And we all were very excited about the idea of sharing this with Howard.
我们想立马告诉他这好消息
We wanted him to hear the news.
我们跳上出租车, 穿过市区, 直奔医院
And then we all jumped in a cab and we raced downtown to St. Vincent's.
我们刚刚开完新闻发布会
We rushed from the press presentation,
一如既往, 发布会尽管简单, 但很成功
which, as rough as it was, was a huge success.
我们兴致火热, 迎来的却是冰冷的噩耗
We were high from it and we came into the cold shock
霍华德病逝了
of Howard dying in a hospital room.
他母亲揭开白布, 让我们看见
His mother pulled back the sheets to show us
他身上穿的美女与野兽的T恤
the Beauty and the Beast sweatshirt that he was wearing.
临终前, 他瘦得皮包骨头, 双眼失明, 气若游丝
He was 80 pounds, had lost his sight and barely had a whisper of a voice.
我们跟他分享了当天令人兴奋的故事
We shared with him what happened that day and how amazing it was.
想着如果他在场该有多好
And how he was there in every way.
之后时间差不多了, 我们一一与他告别
Then, when it was time to leave, we said our goodbyes.
离开前, 我躬身低语道
Before I left, I bent over and whispered,
美女与野兽如今风光无限
Beauty and the Beast was gonna be a great success.
“之前谁能料到呢?”我苦笑着说
"Who'd have thought it?" I said.
仿佛霍华德醒了过来, 低声回应: 我料到了
And Howard lit up and whispered, "I would have."
霍华德于1991年3月14日去世
他未能见到影片完成的样子
盖里•卡尔金当时负责影片推广,
Gary Kalkin, who was running Publicity at the time,
他想到个好主意 一个激进冒险的主意
had a brilliant idea, a scary idea, a dangerous idea that perhaps an unfinished
就是在纽约电影节放映未完成的美女与野兽
work-in-progress screening of Beauty and the Beast could be a part of the New York Film Festival.
后来我们真的放映了这部未完成版
So we actually screened an unfinished version of the film
当时我们都心里没底
and I think we were all on pins and needles.
我们呆坐着, 屏住呼吸
We all were sitting there holding our breath,
因为实在拿不准观众的反应
because we didn't know what kind of reaction there would be.
影片放完后, 片场几乎…
And there was almost-- When the movie ended,
时间几乎停滞了一会儿
it was almost a pause where you went,"1001, 1002,"
然后突然像火山一样爆发了
and then all of a sudden the place just erupted.
当时的我可谓错愕, 震惊
I remember just being absolutely slack-jawed, stunned,
瞠目结舌, 倍感意外
knocked over, goggle-eyed with astonishment.
观众像看百老汇演出一样给予掌声
They applauded like they were at a live Broadway show.
这情形我一辈子都没见过
And I had never seen anything like that in my life.
但现在高兴还为时尚早
It was an emotional roller coaster back home.
美女与野兽还有无数的底稿要画
Beauty and the Beast had thousands of drawings left to go.
阿拉丁的故事情节也遭遇大改
Aladdin was grinding through intense story changes
霍华德之前写的三首歌也不得不弃用
that left three of Howard's songs on the cutting-room floor.
新的歌曲由后来加盟的蒂姆•莱斯负责
And Tim Rice was brought in to finish up the lyrics on the new songs.
任务堆积成山, 而时间有限
The work was intense, the hours were long
唯一的疏解方式就是: 开派对
and there was only one thing that could stop it all: margaritas.
我尝试让自己投入到这个角色
I tried very much to put myself into this character.
这是大家在漫长枯燥的工作之余的减压活动
It was a way for everybody to decompress after the long hours and hideous meetings with Jeffrey.
此时, 我们与同事相处的时间甚至超过陪家人
By this time, we spent more time with each other than with our families.
办公室已经是我们的家
I mean, this was our family.
所以我们好好放松了一下, 吃了点零食
So we'd take a long break, have some chips and salsa,
听了点彼得的鸡汤正能量
and with a little cheerleading from Peter,
就回到了各自的工作
we'd get back on the horse.
太棒了, 我们的团队最牛, 没有之一
It's great. This crew is the best crew. It's fabulous.
- 是不是有点假? - 确实
- Not very sincere, was it? - No.
赞美与功劳始终是重要话题
Credit was always an issue,
人们或是接受赞美
and it seemed that everyone was either taking credit
或不接受, 不赞美
or not getting credit or not giving credit.
那些理应获得掌声的人, 却常被忽视
And the people who really deserved the credit were being overlooked.
也许对这个话题, 我比别人更敏感些
You know, maybe I was more sensitive to that in a way than others might have been,
因为我与沃特还有其他很多人共事过
just because I went through it with Walt and a lot of the guys that worked for him
沃特的光芒如此耀眼
and watched watch them be outshone by so much
而其他人则没有获得应有的灯光和掌声
and not given the kind of credit that they thought they deserved
而这些都是他们应得的
and certainly and in fact that they did.
站在人生的舞台上接受他人的闪光灯, 这很容易
It is easy to get out there on the stage of life and have people shining flashlights at you,
你只需要说: 哇, 不错, 我还行, 对吧?
and you're going, "Wow, yeah, I'm pretty good, aren't I?"
好, 开始
And, action.
大家好, 我是杰弗里•卡岑伯格, 迪斯尼工作室主席
Hi, I'm Jeffrey Katzenberg, chairman of the Walt Disney Studios.
在迪斯尼, 如果我们要拍一部长篇动画
At Disney, when we set out to make an animated feature,
首要的就是寻找特别的故事和性格鲜明的人物
the first thing we look for is a very special story and unforgettable characters.
而美女与野兽就是这样的片子
And that's just what Beauty and the Beast is,
精彩的故事和令人难忘的人物
a great story with unforgettable characters.
停
Cut.
我不在乎荣誉, 完全不在乎
I didn't care about credit. I didn't care about any of that.
人们对我的溢美之词从来没有断过
I had plenty of my own adulation from places I didn't even want it.
不管杰弗里怎样宣传包装自己
The more Jeffrey promoted himself,
只要是为了动画电影好, 我就不反对
as long as he promoted himself around an animated movie, I let it happen.
罗伊则很不爽
Roy went nuts.
大家好, 我是罗伊•迪斯尼
Hello, my name is Roy Disney
很高兴向大家介绍我们全新发售的录像带
and it's my pleasure to introduce the home-video debut
我叔叔沃特电影生涯最杰出的作品
of one of the greatest triumphs of my uncle Walt's filmmaking career:
白雪公主和七个小矮人
Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs.
沃特死后, 有个问题就一直悬而未决
There's always been that question, ever since Walt died:
谁是下一个沃特•迪斯尼?
Who's the next Walt Disney?
媒体需要一个魅力超凡的强势人物
The media demands a central charismatic figure.
我们也需要这种领袖来打开市场
And we demand it to sell our product.
大家好, 我是迈克尔•埃斯纳, 迪斯尼公司的主席
Hello, I'm Michael Eisner, chairman of The Walt Disney Company.
迪斯尼全体希望您能享受这次旅途
All of us here at Disney hope you enjoyed the tour
希望您能够更多地感受电影和电视的魔力
and that it gave you new insight into the magic of motion-picture and television production.
希望能很快再见到您
We hope you come back and see us real soon.
哇噢, 动画工作室这是怎么了?
Whoa, whoa, what is now going on in the studio?
弗兰克, 是我们中间最无私的
Frank, of all of us, was the most selfless,
因此他能够在日益滋长的自满情绪中带领大家
and so he was able to navigate a course between strong and growing personalities and egos.
我觉得弗兰克是我们的中和剂
And I always found Frank the peacemaker, you know,
就像个婚姻顾问一样
that he was like a marriage counselor.
他总是扮演调停者的角色
He was very much of a mediator.
当你有困难, 通常会去找他
He was the person you ran to when you had problems.
有趣的是, 弗兰克的钱包里
Interesting thing about Frank, he carried in his wallet
有张纸条, 写着: 谦逊乃终极美德
a piece of paper that said, "Humility is the ultimate virtue."
通常会有极激进和极保守的方案
You get it from the top and you get it from the bottom
最终还是会选择比较中庸的那个
and are often left floating somewhere in the middle
以保证方向和目标的明确
trying to establish a sense of direction and purpose.
美女与野兽首演那晚, 气氛有一些微妙
It was a delicate balancing act that began to wobble on the night of the Beauty and the Beast premiere.
我愿意做第一个
But I am delighted to be the first,
因为我真心以你们和你们的作品为荣
because I am so enormously proud of all of you and what you pulled off,
不仅仅是美女与野兽这一部电影
not just Beauty and the Beast,
而是整个过去七年
but over the last seven years.
对于当年惊惶的200人来说, 这简直就是奇迹般的转变
It is absolutely a fabulous change from 200 frightened people,
那时, 大家都觉得马上就要丢饭碗
seven years ago, wondering if they were gonna have a job tomorrow.
播放演职员表的时候
At the cast-and-crew screening,
依惯例大家会一一上台发言
there's tradition of everybody getting up and speaking
说些积极正面的话
and saying how great everything is.
我已经皈依这个信仰七年了
It's now been seven years since I was converted to the faith
并且一直在传扬这动画的福音
and I've been preaching the gospel of animation ever since.
直到那晚, 我才意识到
Until that night, I don't think I was aware
迈克尔, 罗伊和杰弗里三人间的敌意有多重
to the extent of the animosity between Michael, Roy and Jeffrey.
大概是1983年, 我接到一个电话
Then about 1983, I got a call.
当时我在佛蒙特米德尔堡参加儿子的夏令营
I was in Middlebury, Vermont, at my son's camp.
接到罗伊•迪斯尼的电话, 他说:
I got a call from Roy Disney, who said,
你有兴趣加盟沃特•迪斯尼公司吗
"Would you be interested in coming to The Walt Disney Company,
因为我想重整旗鼓
because I'd like to keep it together.
否则公司就要分崩离析了
It seems that it's gonna be broken apart."
我说: 嗯, 听起来还不错
And I said, "Well, yeah, that sounds like a good idea."
没错, 当时我坐在第一排的边上
Yeah, and I was sitting right in the very first row in the corner seat,
看着他, 说: 宣布吧, 迈克尔
looking up at him, saying, "Announce it, Michael."
然后迈克尔站起来, 说:
And Michael stood up and said,
为了庆祝这些年了不起的成长
"As part of the reward of this extraordinary growth,
回报大家伟大的付出
the amazing things you've all done,
弗兰克和我同意
Frank and I have agreed to
新建一座动画部大楼
build a new Animation Building on the Disney lot."
而杰弗里是第一次听闻这件事
It was the first time Jeffrey had ever heard that.
那一刻, 我很愤怒, 因为我觉得
In the moment, I was enraged by it, because I felt,
靠, 这帮家伙在搞什么?
"Wow, what are these guys doing here?"
这不合适吧
It was inappropriate.
而言外之意就更深了
And the subtext to that was much, much deeper
绝不仅仅是失礼地宣布建楼
than just the faux pas of announcing a building,
而事先未跟我商量这么简单
you know, without having ever even discussed it with me.
这表明了由来已久的不和谐
And it just showed very deep-seated unhappiness
相互争权, 还有自负之心
and competitiveness and ego.
这完全是一个尊重的问题
It was all about respect.
那晚, 杰弗里希望得到尊重
That night, Jeffrey was looking for the respect
他觉得他理应获得罗伊和迈克尔的尊重
he thought he'd earned from Roy and Michael,
但他没得到
and it just wasn't there.
惊喜两度降临于美女与野兽
Lightning has struck twice with Disney's Beauty and the Beast.
我已经词穷到不知如何形容这部电影了
I'm hard-pressed, had to go to the thesaurus to find all the applicable adjectives:
迷人, 令人陶醉, 扣人心弦, 有魅力…
Enchanting, bewitching, captivating, charming...
美女与野兽获得了巨大的票房成功
Beauty and the Beast opened to huge box office
还是自白雪公主以来最受好评的长篇动画
and probably the most glowing reviews of any animated feature since Snow White.
我陪孩子看了两遍美女与野兽
I've seen Beauty and the Beast twice with my children.
很快我会再看一遍, 这电影太棒了
I'm going to be back for more very soon. It's a winner.
我不敢相信自己有多爱这片子
I was amazed how much I enjoyed this movie.
之前听说它在纽约电影节放映时获得了起立鼓掌
I had heard reports that it played at the New York Film Festival to a standing ovation
- 当时我不相信 - 我也是
- and I questioned those reports. - I did too.
我想说: 我才不信纽约电影节会为任何影片起立鼓掌致敬
I said, "I can't see the New York Film Festival standing up and applauding anything."
看过电影后
Then I saw this movie and
我才见识到其魅力
I heard it interrupted by applause again.
获奖的是:
And the winner is:
奥斯卡提名之前颁发的是金球奖
Before the Oscar nominations came the Golden Globes.
美女与野兽
Beauty and the Beast,
迪斯尼电影公司制作, 博伟影业发行
Walt Disney Pictures, Buena Vista Pictures Distribution.
当念到我们的名字时
When they announced our name,
我正坐在离舞台最远的桌旁
I was sitting at what had to have been the furthest table from the stage,
我身后就是会场服务人员了
back with the busboys and the valet-parking guys.
这个奖是我们始料未及的, 来自好莱坞的肯定
But this was a validation from Hollywood that we'd never really seen before.
也许, 只是也许,
And maybe, just maybe,
这意味着动画片不再是小孩子过家家了
this meant that animation was no longer at the kids' card table in the kitchen.
我们为杰弗里赢得了票房
We'd won the Bank of America award for Jeffrey
为艺术家们赢得了金球奖
and now the Golden Globe for the artists.
而锦上添花的还在后面
The icing on the cake was yet to come.
噢, 非常感谢
Oh, thank you very much.
刚才想必很多电视机前的动画师都乐坏了吧
A lot of animators just tossed their hot dogs and popcorn in the air at home.
所以这个奖真是大快人心
So you've made some people very, very happy.
- 我很荣幸宣布 - 好
- I'm pleased to announce - Good.
1991年获得最佳影片提名的是:
that the motion pictures selected as the Best Picture nominee of 1991 are:
美女与野兽, 出品人: 唐•哈恩
Beauty and the Beast, Don Hahn, producer.
美女与野兽获得了六项提名
Beauty and the Beast got six nominations,
包括最佳影片的提名
including a nomination for Best Picture.
这确实创造了一项记录
Now that really sets a record here,
因为在迪斯尼历史上
because in the history of Disney,
仅有两部电影得过最佳影片提名
Disney has only had Best Picture nominees twice,
一部是欢乐满人间, 另一部是死亡诗社
once for Mary Poppins and once for the Dead Poets Society.
因此这对美女与野兽而言, 是巨大的荣誉
So that was a great honor for Beauty and the Beast.
我们听说美女与野兽获提名时
When we first heard that Beauty was nominated,
仿佛有一道电流传遍整个工作室
it was like an electrical charge that went through the entire studio.
我整个人都疯狂了
I just came unglued.
真的就穿着内裤跳起舞来
I did a dance around the house in my underwear.
那一天我的电话一直响个不停
And my phone just rang for the rest of the day.
贺信, 贺电不断, 门前堆满各种糖果
Congratulatory messages and telegrams and boxes of candy were showing up at my door.
简直太疯狂了
It was nuts.
真是我美妙的一天
I was queen for a day.
我们穿着租来的燕尾服和晚装
We came to the Oscars in our rented tuxedos and fancy ball gowns
我脑子一片空白, 想着: 我们是怎么来到这里的?
and all I could think of was, "How did we get here?"
获得奥斯卡奖的是:
And the Oscar goes to:
沉默的羔羊
The Silence of the Lambs.
好吧, 那晚我们没有获奖
Well, we didn't win that night,
但之后的舞会真是太棒了
but, boy, did we get invited to the ball.
第二天, 我们又回到工作
The next day, it was back to work.
- 嗨, 伙计 - 嗨, 罗恩
- Hi there. - Hi, Ron.
再介绍一下, 这是罗恩•克莱门茨
This is Ron Clements, once more.
他已经搬出了之前的小办公室
He moved out of his tiny little room.
- 正忙什么呢? - 阿拉丁
- What are you working on right now? - Aladdin.
这些是阿拉丁的草稿, 估计又要得奥斯卡了
These are sketches from Aladdin, another Academy Award winner.
谁知道呢, 对吧?过几年才会知道吧
Who knows, you know? You'll know better a few years from now.
阿拉丁的制作
By the time Aladdin came,
像马拉松一样, 考验的是生理的强度
the animation marathon was really beginning to tell on the physical strength,
完全拼的是体力和耐力
I mean, just in terms of endurance.
感觉就像: 怎么样, 长跑觉得怎么样?
Now there was this, "Okay, how are you in the long run?
还能坚持吗?
Can you keep going?"
很多设计师得了腕管综合症
Many of the artists had physical problems with their carpel tunnel syndrome.
记得有一天, 那天正好是赎罪日
And I remember on one day, it was the Day of Atonement.
杰弗里走进工作室
Jeffrey came to the studio
叫大家跟他一起坐下
and asked everybody to sit down with him
然后说说与他共事的感想
and just tell him what it was like to work with him.
他说: 尽管实话实说
And he said, "Just be honest with me."
于是大家开始吐槽迪斯尼工作的真实想法
People started to share what working at Disney Animation was really like.
有些人无法成立家庭
Some people couldn't have a family,
因为如此重压之下很难抚养孩子
because they really had no way of being able to raise kids in this kind of pressure.
而我, 端着咖啡杯, 手都会抖
For me, holding a coffee cup, my hand would shake,
抖得非常厉害
was just shaking so badly,
因为前一晚我通宵在做动画
because I'd been animating the whole night before.
这是我唯一一次见杰弗里眼泛泪光
It was the only time that I had seen Jeffrey with a tear in his eyes
他为如此逼迫动画师们感到自责
from just being moved by what he was pushing the artists to do.
他还说: 这样不对, 你们必须有正常的生活
And he said, "This is not right. You have to have a life."
但是一切照旧, 实际上, 我们更忙了
Nothing changed. In fact, it got busier.
本来怪罪到杰弗里或迈克尔的逼迫是合情合理的
And it would have been easy to blame Jeffrey or Michael for pushing hard,
因为他们确实如此, 但要知道
because they were, but, you know,
艺术家们也在给自己施压
the truth is that the artists were pushing just as hard.
获奖捷报频频传来
The rewards were pouring in,
我们必须不断超越自己
so we all kept trying to top ourselves.
一时间, 奖金领到手软
Suddenly, there were bonuses
停车场也挤满了宝马和保时捷
and the parking lot was just full of BMWs and Porsches.
我们建起了新办公楼
We were getting a new building
我们开始有律师和经纪人, 开始参加脱口秀节目
and people were getting lawyers and agents and appearing on talk shows.
因为人们的注意力通常是眼睛
You always look into somebody's eyes
作画时, 如果犯错了
and if you're going to make a mistake in the drawing,
- 千万别出在眼睛上 - 没错
- don't let it be in the eyes. - Right.
这是大家所看重的地方
That's where everybody's reading it.
很有意思, 我本人作为画师, 也很明白
It's interesting, because that was also, personally as an artist,
当薪水上涨
when our salaries went up.
当大家都成了明星
When everybody became rock stars.
一切都仿佛不可阻挡
When it looked like you couldn't stop it.
尽管有所牺牲, 吃冷饭, 没时间陪家人
Even with the sacrifice, the cold dinners, the nights away from family,
我们仍像是活在梦里
we were living the dream.
- 涨, 涨工资 - 剪了这段
- Raises. More money. - Cut that.
迪斯尼成了动画界的圣地
Disney became the place to be for animation.
昔日员工如蒂姆•伯顿和亨利•塞利克回到工作室
Alumni like Tim Burton and Henry Selick returned to the studio
制作定格动画, 片名为: 圣诞夜惊魂
to make a stop-motion movie, The Nightmare Before Christmas.
彼得试图从皮克斯挖来约翰•拉赛特
And Peter tried to hire John Lasseter away from Pixar,
但约翰坚持留在这家处境艰难的初创公司
but John insisted on staying with the struggling start-up company.
彼得只好与约翰达成协议
So Peter struck a deal with John
由约翰执导合拍一部电脑动画
to direct a computer-animated co-production with Disney,
这是业界首创, 片名叫做: 玩具总动员
the first of its kind, a buddy picture called Toy Story.
当时在佛罗里达已经有子工作室了
There was already a satellite studio in Florida
而巴黎的另一家子工作室正在制作高飞的电影
and now production started on A Goofy Movie at another studio in Paris.
百老汇也开始排演美女与野兽的舞台剧
Rehearsals began on the new Broadway production of Beauty and the Beast.
五年之前, 工作室的精力只够完成一部电影
Five years earlier, the care and focus was on one picture at a time,
而现在是五部电影和一部百老汇歌剧
and now there were five movies and a Broadway show
而且进展神速
in very active production.
大家都觉得心力交瘁
Everybody was spread too thin.
我才不在乎我是谁, 反正我自由了
I don't care what I am. I'm free!
制造虚空可是违法的, 哈哈哈！
Offer void where prohibited by law. Ha-ha-ha!
主人, 我觉得你还不太明白你所拥有的
Master, I don't think you quite realize what you got here.
阿拉丁揭开了1992年感恩节长假的序幕
Aladdin opened on Thanksgiving weekend, 1992.
这是第一部票房超过两亿美元的动画片
It was the first animated feature to gross over $200 million.
这些影片再次成为了迪斯尼公司的心脏与灵魂
These movies became the heart and soul, once again, of The Walt Disney Company.
全公司围绕影片展开业务, 比如销售周边
The entire company rallied around them, sold merchandising,
电视转播费, 策划特别项目
put them on TV, made specials about them,
将人物加进主题公园, 加入公园游行队伍
became characters in the park, became rides in the park.
这是一段令人陶醉的黄金时代
It was an extraordinarily heady period of time.
我们简直无往不利, 点石成金
We could do no wrong. Everything we touched turned to gold.
电影票房屡创新高
Every movie was bigger than the last movie.
很乐意见到人们开始…
And it was great just to see people--
陈旧的观念 -- 动画片只是给小孩看的
The stigma of animation being just a kids' medium
被这几部影片改变了
kind of get peeled away by these various films.
我们庆祝阿拉丁成功的时候
While we celebrated the success of Aladdin,
下一部影片的制作也开始了
the next movie was bearing down on us.
这是个被称为非洲斑比的有些老套的故事
It was a coming-of-age story that everyone called Bambi in Africa.
记得曾经看过一部纪录片, 片名是
I remember having seen a documentary called
永恒的敌人: 狮子与土狼
The Eternal Enemies: Lions and Hyenas.
这片子紧张刺激, 充满力量和戏剧性
I mean, it was so incredibly powerful and dramatic and intense.
我想: 若我们的电影能够还原
And I thought, "Wow, if this movie could capture,
这纪录片的震撼力, 将会妙不可言
you know, a tenth of the power of this documentary, then it would be terrific.
他在打招呼, 他在跟你打招呼
He's just saying hello. He's saying hello to you, by the way.
你看他们非常依赖触感
You notice that they are very contact-oriented.
他跑到人脚边然后…
He just walked under this man's leg just then.
今天, 这黄色胶带真的代表警戒小心
And in this case, the yellow caution tape really does mean caution.
影片制作了几个月后
We'd been working on it for a couple of months,
杰弗里组织了一次早餐会
and then Jeffrey calls a breakfast meeting.
风中奇缘和狮子王的制作人员全数参会
And in the meeting, we have the whole crew from Pocahontas and Lion King.
杰弗里说: 风中奇缘就像全垒打
And Jeffrey says, "Pocahontas is a home run.
这是个西区故事
It's West Side Story,
是北美印第安版的罗密欧与朱丽叶
it's Romeo and Juliet with American Indians.
它必然会成功, 注定不会失败
It's a hit. It's got hit written all over it.
至于狮子王, 只能算是试验之作吧
Lion King, on the other hand, is kind of an experiment.
我们真不确定人们是否会喜欢
We don't really know if anybody's gonna really wanna see it."
那次会后
And after that meeting,
当然无人愿意参与制作狮子王了
absolutely no one wanted to work on Lion King.
没人对狮子王有信心, 这实际上…
No one had any faith in that movie, which is, actually--
谈到狮子王阐释的道理, 应该是: 人皆有可取之处
If there's a lesson in The Lion King, it's "Nobody knows nothing."
开篇辛巴出现在一片荫蔽的林地
We start with Simba in a secluded glade.
他好像在思考人生
He's kind of contemplating life,
他抬头望着天空和星星, 然后…
when he looks up and sees the stars and is reminded...
故事的核心观念是我想出来的
The kernel of that idea is something that actually originated with me.
人的一生总会有那些关键的时刻
It was really about that moment in each of our lives
突然间我们会长大并学会担当责任
in which we sort of have to grow up and take responsibility.
在生命的轨迹上找到自己的位置
We have to take our place in the circle of life.
这是一则关于年轻人承担使命和未来的寓言
It's allegorically a young person born with a future that's to be fulfilled,
他历经劫难到达目的地
who has to go through a lot of difficulties to get there,
更重要的是, 他学会了相信自己
and most especially, who has to learn to believe in himself
然后成功地完成了使命
before he can become what he is fated to be.
这是充满莎翁色彩的关于领袖责任的故事
It became more and more this Shakespearean tale about the responsibilities of leadership.
很诡异的是, 它更像是一部自传
And in a really strange way, it seemed almost autobiographical,
讲述了激烈竞争男权社会里边缘人的崛起
all about the brinksmanship that can arise in this competitive male environment.
我走出剧本讨论会场, 直奔弗兰克办公室
I came out of a story meeting and ran right into Frank Wells.
他问我: 狮子王进展得怎么样了?
And he asked me, "How are things going on The Lion King?"
我说: 棒极了
I said, "Great.
简直是在拍摄我们自己的故事
We're making a movie about ourselves."
你的经历, 就是一段迪斯尼传奇
It's a Disney fantasy, your life.
当时, 我从没想过会成为公司CEO
At the moment. I never thought I would be a CEO of a company.
从没想过会掌管迪斯尼
I never thought I would run Disney.
我希望此刻能够永恒
I'd like to freeze everything right now.
我想冻结时间, 我不想老去, 我热爱我的年纪
I'd like to just freeze. I'd like to stay my age. I like my age.
热爱妻子的年纪, 孩子的年纪
I like my wife's age. I like my children's age.
我很满意迪斯尼的运营现状
I like the way Disney is going.
我希望冻结此刻的人生
I'd like to freeze my life right now.
那是1994年的复活节礼拜日
It was Easter Sunday, 1994.
内华达宝石山上发生的一件事
And a single event in Nevada's Ruby Mountains
引发了一连串意想不到的变化
would set in motion an unimaginable chain of events.
直升机坠入峡谷约一英里处
The helicopter had flown approximately a mile down the canyon
然后撞在山腰7200尺位置
before it crashed into a rugged hillside at approximately 7,200 feet.
这是公司史上唯一一次直升机失事造成死亡
This is the only helicopter crash and the first fatality in the company's history.
弗兰克·威尔斯葬礼
愿我们共同分担此刻的悲伤
There are some griefs that have to be shared.
共同分享此刻的喜悦
Likewise, there are some joys so overwhelming that they should be shared as well.
我们为弗兰克的离世而感怀
And while we all give Frank's death and grieve it,
为此生有幸与他相识而欣喜
we all share the joy of having known Frank.
今天, 我们在此缅怀
That is why we are here today, to remember--
缅怀, 歌颂和赞美一个拥有创意人生,
To remember and to celebrate, to pay tribute to one man who had magic
并乐意与人分享魔法的魔术师
and to share the magic with him through his whole creative life.
今天会场放的歌曲和音乐
The songs and music you have heard and will hear today
不是哀乐或挽歌
are not the songs of music of sorrow or of death.
而是弗兰克钟爱的歌曲
They are the songs that Frank Wells enjoyed--
是他钟爱一声的歌曲
These are the songs that Frank enjoyed during his life.
下面我要介绍
I would now like to introduce the man
将我和弗兰克引入迪斯尼的人: 罗伊•迪斯尼
who thought up Frank and me for this job, Roy Disney.
就这么多?
That was it?
再补一句
My speaker's off.
他是一个天马行空, 了不起, 不可思议的人
This is a fantastic, wonderful, unbelievable human being.
对吧?
Okay?
好的
Okay.
弗兰克是这帮自大狂中间的调和剂
Frank was the peacemaker amongst all these tremendous egos.
他死后, 大家不知找谁倾诉
And when Frank died, there was no one to talk to.
不知道该说什么
Nobody knew what to say.
工作室笼罩着一种奇异的寂静
It was a very strange quietness that overcame the studio,
大家心中在问: 现在怎么办?
just wondering, "Now what?"
这是一只幼狮
And that is a little baby cub.
现在看来非常可爱
And he is just the cutest thing.
但将来会长成750磅的大家伙
And this guy is gonna grow up to be 750 pounds.
弗兰克死后
Ever since Frank's death,
杰弗里试图接手弗兰克公司董事长的职位
Jeffrey was lobbying for Frank's job as president of the company,
但罗伊不会坐视不管
but Roy wouldn't have anything to do with it.
他已经对杰弗里频繁亮相发布会颇有微词
He already felt uncomfortable with the amount of press that Jeffrey was getting.
我一直在领导这些电影制作
I was out front on these movies.
我一直在卖力宣传
I was selling the films.
电影越成功, 大家就越关注我
The more successful they were, the more attention came to me,
进而我又能为影片获得更多关注
the more I was able to get attention for the films.
他有点焦躁不安了, 快点拍
He's getting restless, so shoot away.
很好, 潘乔, 太棒了, 潘乔
Great, good. Pancho, good. Pancho.
当时, 我想很多人都好奇
At the time, I think many people felt,
我这么做是对公司领袖的职位有所企图吗?
well, am I doing this for me and my own career?
我想迈克尔在方面对我构成很大竞争
I think Michael became very competitive with me at some point in this.
他不满我所获得的关注和认同
He was uncomfortable with the amount of attention and recognition that I was getting for it.
罗伊应该也是非常不爽
I think Roy was extremely uptight about it.
一天, 杰弗里带着一名华尔街日报记者来到公司
Jeffrey was gonna come in with a reporter from The Wall Street Journal
记者在公司参观, 观察我们的电影制作过程
and he was gonna follow us around to show how the movie got made.
杰弗里亲自做了一些展示
And Jeffrey performed for the journalist
我们也演示了一小段电影制作的真实过程
and we created what looked like a slice of how the movie actually got made.
那篇报道中, 杰弗里被夸赞为迪斯尼动画的救世主
And in that article, Jeffrey was proclaimed the guy who was saving Disney Animation.
我觉得这件事让我真的忍无可忍了
I think that was kind of a last-straw kind of a thing for me.
我感到很愤怒
I was just incensed by that.
这就是迪斯尼动画引以为豪的信条:
This is the vaunted Walt Disney Company's animation machine in action:
团结协作, 勇于挑战, 精益求精, 细致严苛
collaborative, confrontational, extravagant, exacting,
工作室在卡岑伯格先生事无巨细的经营下,
and under the meddlesome, protective hand of Mr. Katzenberg,
取得了辉煌的成就
wildly successful.
三十年代, 迪斯尼开创了动画电影这一类型
The studio that invented the animated movie in the 1930s,
后来曾一度低迷, 但如今已重回巅峰
but stumbled badly in the past decades, is back with a vengeance.
近些年, 它制作了一系列无可匹敌的重磅大作
It has produced an unparalleled string of blockbusters,
从小美人鱼到美女与野兽, 到阿拉丁
from The Little Mermaid to Beauty and the Beast to Aladdin.
实际上, 若考虑电影相关的周边商品
In fact, counting ancillary activities like merchandising,
音箱制品和主题公园
video sales and theme-park attractions,
迪斯尼的动画电影
Disney's animated movies are simply
将是娱乐产业有史以来最成功的产品
the most successful products in the history of the entertainment business.
拉斯维加斯周日晚间上演了
It was the president of Walt Disney Studios
迪斯尼老总对阵丛林之王的好戏
versus the king of the jungle in Las Vegas Sunday night.
有惊无险, 杰弗里•卡岑伯格没有命丧狮口
And luckily, Jeffrey Katzenberg can live to laugh about it.
其实, 我知道最后的…
You know, the final moment that was literally--
不出意料
And I knew it, the day it happened.
压死骆驼的最后一根稻草
the straw that broke the camel's back is
是里奇•特纳发表在华尔街日报上关于狮子王的文章
there was an article that Rich Turner wrote in The Wall Street Journal about Lion King.
很有意思, 那天我早上起床
And it was so interesting, because when I got up in the morning,
看了那份报纸, 真是一大清早
I read the paper, you know, very early in the morning
我还记得出门去上班前我对太太说:
and I remember saying to Marilyn before I left for work, I said,
一切都完了, 这文章太要命了
"Well, this is over. This is the nail in my coffin."
距离正点还有22分钟
It is now 22 minutes before the hour.
我已经50多岁了, 但每当迪斯尼出新片,
I'm over 50 years old and every time Disney comes out with a new animated movie,
我都迫不及待地一睹为快
I rush off to see it.
本周我们将在读感受迪斯尼的魔力
And all this week, we're gonna be looking at the magic
他们的新片即将上映
that has created the new Disney animated feature.
片名为: 狮子王
It is called The Lion King.
你们在不断尝试, 试验
So you all test this, these things.
说说吧, 能否稍微透露一下
Tell me, give me a little-- Give me a taste.
你们用狮子王做了哪些试验?
What is the test on The Lion King?
首先我不相信科研, 从不
First of all, we don't believe in research. I never have.
- 真的吗? - 真的
- Really? - Never.
竟然有人说, 这是我们有史以来最大胆的试验之作
That being said, it's the highest-tested film we have ever had.
很自豪能够成为制作组的成员
I'm very proud to be part of it.
很荣幸能够参与延续迪斯尼动画的光辉传统
And to be proud part of that great tradition of Disney animated features.
哈库纳玛塔塔, 毫无疑问
Hakuna matata, which of course,
是斯瓦希里语“5亿全球票房”的意思
in Swahili, means"500 million worldwide."
实际上, 哈库纳玛塔塔是斯瓦希里语“无忧无虑”的意思
Actually, hakuna matata, in Swahili, does mean" No worries."
不过, 鉴于狮子王红到发紫的热度
And, boy, judging from the success of The Lion King,
说5亿票房也毫不为过
it is safe to say that at this point,
迪斯尼动画工作室这回真的可以高枕无忧了
Disney Studios, which made the movie, has hakuna matata.
现在是洛杉矶现场发回的报道
We're live from Los Angeles.
现在上红地毯的是马修•布罗德里克
And here coming up on the red carpet is Matthew Broderick.
四年前, 我们下决心要拍好这部电影
About four years ago, we all decided we were gonna make it,
之后, 我们开始全身心投入
and so, you know, you fall in love pretty soon after that.
四年前, 我们还心里没底 不过现在, 信心满满
So four years ago, I would say, "Well, yeah," But now, it's great.
狮子王在好莱坞的首映礼上
By the time The Lion King premiered in Hollywood,
媒体已经注意到了一些紧张情绪
the press had picked up on the tensions
当时杰弗里谢绝了红毯上的所有采访
and Jeffrey waved off all interviews on the red carpet.
一次迈克尔与我共进午餐, 他对我说:
I had lunch with Michael and, you know, he said to me,
我不再支持你接任弗兰克了
"I'm not interested in having you take this job.
虽然我曾许诺过你会得到升迁
Even though I said I was and promised you that you were,
但我改主意了
I've changed my mind."
然后我对他说: 好, 我明白
And I said to him, "Fine, I understand.
既然你改变主意, 也下了决心
But, you know, in changing your mind and deciding to do it,
也意味着, 我在此地已走到尽头
you know, it really says to me I have no future here."
杰弗里很有才干, 但他走错了棋
Jeffrey was a very good executive. He just played it wrong.
如果他安于工作室的岗位, 尽忠职守
Had he been happy to stay at the studio, stay in his job,
而不是在人尸骨未寒之际, 急于上位
not push everybody against the wall at a moment when somebody had died,
他早晚会得到那份职位
he would have gotten the job,
他只需要稍微耐心一些
had he just had the patience to wait.
- 你随时可以说了 - 开始拍了?
- Whenever you're comfortable. - You are rolling?
- 是的 - 好
- Yeah. - Okay.
公司众多业务中…
With all the many varied businesses this company is in, it is...
剧组首次发布会就要到来了
The cast-and-crew premiere was coming up fast.
依惯例, 我们会一一登台
It was tradition for all of us to get up on-stage
发表一番感谢辞
and give warm thank-you speeches.
但这次, 我决定用摄影机拍下大家的感谢辞
But this time, I decided to film all the speeches instead.
这些年完成了一些不可思议的任务
-an unbelievable job over the last decade,
狮子王是一座高峰, 我们将继续向前…
culminating in Lion King, and pushing forward...
不久后, 迈克尔突然胸口疼
Soon after, Michael complained of chest pains
被紧急送往医院
and was rushed to the hospital
在那里他接受了心脏搭桥手术
where he underwent quadruple bypass surgery.
这个, 我得… 我还没缓过神
All right, I gotta just-- Mind on other things.
他招募弗兰克和迈克尔进公司十年后
Ten years after he ushered Frank and Michael into the company,
动画业务已如日中天
and with Animation at the height of success,
而公司内部却隐忧重重
the wheels were coming off the car.
刚才没拍到, 对吧
You're not rolling, I hope.
开始吧
Anytime.
我想衷心感谢你们每一位
Well, I just wanna personally say thank you to everybody
你们再次创造了奇迹, 希望能再接再厉
for another absolutely incredible job on another marvelous movie
再创辉煌
on the way to the next great movie.
十年前, 我们刚来迪斯尼时
Ten years ago, when we arrived here at Disney
罗伊抓着迈克尔和我的手
and Roy took Michael and I in hand
领着我们走进动画部大楼二楼
over to the second floor of the Animation Building,
在那里, 罗恩和约翰
and with Ron and John,
向我们从头到尾展示了老鼠神探的原始故事构思
walked us through those initial storyboards for The Great Mouse Detective,
当时的我, 打破头也想象不到
there's not a chance in the world that with all the imagination I could muster
十年后, 此时此地的景象
that I could envision ten years later being here
十年间, 制作了各色影片, 与人谈业务合作, 经历过荣耀
and having the kinds of movies, collaboration and pride
作为迪斯尼动画这一卓越团队的一员, 我深感骄傲
that I feel having been a part of this extraordinary team called Disney Feature Animation.
对我来说, 这份荣耀令日复一日的工作不再单调
For me, it is what makes coming to work every day so special.
对于镜头前的大家, 我无法表达
And to all of you, I'm not sure I can ever tell you how much it means
我有多热爱成为你们家庭的一分子
and how much I love being part of your family.
我很骄傲能够参与制作这些世上最优秀的电影
And how proud I am to have been a part of these movies with the best in the world.
谢谢
Thank you.
狮子王上映后, 他辞职了
After the opening of The Lion King, he resigned.
随便去研究所, 大学,
Go to any institution, any university,
医院, 公司, 家庭, 房子看看
any hospital, any corporation, any home, any house.
知道吗?
You know what?
人的光辉永远会盖过屋宇的光鲜华美
The human condition overshadows bricks and mortar every time.
人类生活的主题永远是恐惧, 嫉妒, 安慰
And it's about fear and envy and jealousy and comfort
还有爱恨与满足
and love and hate and accomplishment.
任何地方都是如此
Every institution has it.
我们是不是一帮感情用事
Were we a bunch of artistic, emotional people
疯疯癫癫, 吵吵闹闹的所谓艺术家呢?
running around, screaming and crying and ranting and raving?
当然不, 实际上我们井井有条, 紧密协作, 我们常说:
No, it was an organized group of people working together, saying,
我们来露两手吧
"Let's put on a show."
曲终人散, 夜深人静之际
After all that drama, the late nights,
唯余残羹冷炙, 受挫的心灵
the cold pizza, the bruised egos
还有疏离于家庭的时光
and all those hours away from family,
最终, 无人能忆起这恩怨情仇, 是非种种
in the end, nobody will remember who did what to who,
不朽的是剧中角色,
but they will remember the characters
他们生于画笔, 活于荧幕, 却永驻人心
who leapt from a pencil onto the screen and into the hearts of the audience,
一切亦本应如此
and that's how it should be.
迪斯尼卡通的魔力是举世无双的
I just don't think anything is quite as magical as a Disney cartoon fairy tale.
它完全不可复制
There's just nothing like that.
下面是影片大结局
And now the grand finale.
- 琳达, 没憋着吧? - 没事
- Linda, do you have enough air? - Yeah?
敢动我试试 这里的感觉很棒
Try me. Just it feels great to be here.
我俩都喝高了, 给关进了牢里
We were both riotously drunk and we were thrown in jail.
好的, 高飞, 到你表演了
Okay, Goofy, let's see what you got.
我就知道没好事
I knew something was up.
放我出去, 放我出去
Let me out of here. Let me out.
嗨, 我们现在以时速130公里
Hi. We're going 130 kilometers per hour here
穿行在法国乡间, 而且我没穿内裤
through the French countryside and I'm not wearing any pants.
迪斯尼, 最牛
Disney, number one.
我喜欢这里
I love it here!
好, 准备好了吗?先模仿伯吉斯•梅雷迪斯?
Okay, ready? Burgess Meredith first?
来吧, 阿拉丁
Come on, Aladdin.
别管我说的什么, 只管跟我走！
I don't know what I'm saying. Just go with me!
我还是有点害羞
I'm kind of a little self-conscious.
差不多时间到了
It's about time it's coming out.
瞧
See here.
噢, 我的胸大肌
Oh, my breast.
罗杰没有弱点
Roger has no weak spots.
我1945年入行 没错, 你就是四棒的脑残粉
I started in 1945. Yes, I called you the kiss-ass of cleanup.
噢, 天呐, 我说太多了
Oh, dear, I've said too much.
讲之前我想问个问题先
I'm gonna ask you a question before I continue.
我能提杰弗里•卡岑伯格的大名吗?
Am I allowed to mention Jeffrey Katzenberg?
让他穿件毛衣不就得了
Tell him just to put a sweater on.
我忘词了
I'm stuck for the rest of it.